<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="bitext.css" type="text/css"?>
<bitext version="1.2">
<segments>
<seg  match="1-1" id="1">
  <src xml:lang="EN">﻿WIPO</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">﻿ WIPO</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="2">
  <src xml:lang="EN">E</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">C</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="3">
  <src xml:lang="EN">WO/GA/31/1</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">WO/GA/31/1</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="4">
  <src xml:lang="EN">ORIGINAL: English</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">原  文 ： 英 文 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="5">
  <src xml:lang="EN">DATE: June 28, 2004</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">日  期 ： 2004年 6月 28日 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="6">
  <src xml:lang="EN">WORLD INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY ORGANIZATION</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">世  界  知  识  产  权  组  织 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="7">
  <src xml:lang="EN">GENEVA</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">日  内  瓦 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="8">
  <src xml:lang="EN">wipo general assembly</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">世  界  知  识  产  权  组  织  大  会 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="9">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Thirty-First (15th Extraordinary) Session</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">第  三  十 一 届  会  议  ( 第  15 次  特  别  会  议  )</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="10">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Geneva, September 27 to October 5, 2004</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">2004 年  9 月  27 日  至  10 月  5 日 ， 日  内  瓦 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="11">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Report on the Policy Advisory Commission (PAC)</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">政 策 顾 问 委 员 会 (PAC)的 报 告 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="8-6" id="12">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Memorandum of the Director General<br/>1 The Assemblies of the Member States of WIPO approved, in their thirty-second series of meetings, from March 25 to 27, 1998, the proposal contained in the 1998-1999 biennial Program and Budget to establish the Policy Advisory Commission (PAC), comprised of eminent individuals from a wide range of policy backgrounds.<br/>It was noted that<br/>"the policy-making and medium-term planning processes of WIPO, its responsiveness to international trends and technological developments, and its capacity to anticipate and to meet the needs of the market sector and users of global protection systems, would benefit considerably from the availability of informed and objective advice from eminent international experts from a broad range of fields with bearing on intellectual property cooperation and WIPO’s operations” (see document A/32/2 - WO/BC/18/2,<br/>Sub-program 01.3).<br/>2 The mandate of this independent advisory body was defined in the same document<br/>(see Sub-program 01.3) and reaffirmed in the most recent Program and Budget of the Organization (see document WO/PBC/7/2, Sub-program 02.2), which states that the PAC will "continue to provide objective and informed external expert advice to the Director General, particularly with respect to policy-making, medium-term planning, processes and the needs in the market sector”.<br/>3 It should be noted that the role of the Policy Advisory Commission is strictly advisory and consultative and shall "never replace or diminish the role of the Member States in the initiation and monitoring of the program of the Organization” (see document A/32/2 - WO/BC/18/2, Sub-program 01.3).<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">总 干 事 备 忘 录 <br/>1. WIPO成 员 国 大 会 在 1998年 3月 25日 至 27日 举 行 的 第 三 十 二 届 系 列 会 议 上 ， 批 准 了 1998－ 1999两 年 期 计 划 和 预 算 中 所 载 的 关 于 成 立 由 具 有 广 泛 政 策 背 景 的 知 名 人 士 组 成 的 政 策 顾 问 委 员 会 (PAC)的 建 议 。 <br/>该 建 议 指 出 "世 界 知 识 产 权 组 织 的 决 策 与 中 期 规 划 进 程 ， 其 对 国 际 趋 势 和 技 术 进 步 的 反 应 ， 及 其 预 测 和 满 足 市 场 部 门 和 全 球 保 护 体 系 用 户 的 需 求 的 能 力 ， 均 将 因 有 来 自 与 知 识 产 权 合 作 和 本 组 织 业 务 有 关 的 广 泛 领 域 的 知 名 国 际 专 家 提 供 有 见 地 的 客 观 咨 询 意 见 而 受 益 匪 浅 ” (见 文 件 A/32/2－ WO/BC/18/2分 项 计 划 01.3)。 <br/>2. 在 同 一 文 件 中 确 定 了 该 独 立 顾 问 机 构 的 任 务 (见 分 项 计 划 01.3)， 本 组 织 最 近 的 计 划 和 预 算 又 对 其 加 以 确 认 (见 WO/PBC/7/2分 项 计 划 02.2)。 <br/>该 计 划 和 预 算 中 称 ， 政 策 顾 问 委 员 会 将 "确 定 并 全 面 审 查 可 能 需 由 本 组 织 处 理 或 与 其 业 务 有 关 的 问 题 ， 并 为 如 何 加 强 政 策 发 展 和 本 组 织 业 务 提 出 建 议 ” 。 <br/>3. 应 该 指 出 的 是 ， 该 委 员 会 的 作 用 严 格 地 属 于 顾 问 和 咨 询 性 质 ， "在 启 动 和 监 测 本 组 织 的 计 划 方 面 ， 绝 对 不 能 取 代 或 削 弱 各 成 员 国 的 作 用 ” （ 见 文 件 A/32/2－ WO/BC/18/2分 项 计 划 01.3） 。 <br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="13">
  <src xml:lang="EN">4 The fourth meeting of the PAC took place on November 14, 2003, in Sinaia, Romania.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">4. 政 策 顾 问 委 员 会 第 四 次 会 议 于 2003年 11月 14日 在 罗 马 尼 亚 锡 纳 亚 举 行 。 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="14">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Twenty members attended the meeting, and its report to the Director General of WIPO is contained in Annex I.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">共 有 20名 成 员 出 席 会 议 ， 其 向 WIPO总 干 事 提 交 的 报 告 载 于 附 件 一 中 。 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="15">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The list of participants at the meeting is contained in Annex II.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">与 会 者 名 单 载 于 附 件 二 中 。 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="16">
  <src xml:lang="EN">5 The General Assembly is invited to note and comment on the present document and the report to the Director General of WIPO.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">5. 请 大 会 注 意 本 文 件 和 向 WIPO总 干 事 提 交 的 报 告 的 内 容 ， 并 就 其 发 表 意 见 。 </tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="17">
  <src xml:lang="EN">[Annex I follows]</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="ZH">[后 接 附 件 一 ]</tgt>
</seg>
</segments>
</bitext>
