<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="bitext.css" type="text/css"?>
<bitext version="1.2">
<segments>
<seg  match="1-1" id="1">
  <src xml:lang="EN">THE LITTLE PRINCE</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">LE PETIT PRINCE</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="2">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Antoine De Saint-Exupery</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Antoine de Saint-Exupéry</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="3">
  <src xml:lang="EN">1943</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">1943</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="4">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Once when I was six years old I saw a magnificent picture in a book, called True Stories from Nature, about the primeval forest.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Lorsque j’avais six ans j’ai vu, une fois, une magnifique image, dans un livre sur la Forêt Vierge qui s’appelait ' Histoires Vécues '.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="5">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was a picture of a boa constrictor in the act of swallowing an animal.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça représentait un serpent boa qui avalait un fauve.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="6">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Here is a copy of the drawing.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Voilà la copie du dessin.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="20-21" id="7">
  <src xml:lang="EN">In the book it said: "Boa constrictors swallow their prey whole, without chewing it.<br/>After that they are not able to move, and they sleep through the six months that they need for digestion.”<br/>I pondered deeply, then, over the adventures of the jungle.<br/>And after some work with a coloured pencil I succeeded in making my first drawing.<br/>My Drawing Number One.<br/>It looked like this:<br/>I showed my masterpiece to the grown-ups, and asked them whether the drawing frightened them.<br/>But they answered: "Frighten?<br/>Why should any one be frightened by a hat?”<br/>My drawing was not a picture of a hat.<br/>It was a picture of a boa constrictor digesting an elephant.<br/>But since the grownups were not able to understand it, I made another drawing: I drew the inside of the boa constrictor, so that the grown-ups could see it clearly.<br/>They always need to have things explained.<br/>My Drawing Number Two looked like this:<br/>The grown-ups’ response, this time, was to advise me to lay aside my drawings of boa constrictors, whether from the inside or the outside, and devote myself instead to geography, history, arithmetic and grammar.<br/>That is why, at the age of six, I gave up what might have been a magnificent career as a painter.<br/>I had been disheartened by the failure of my Drawing Number One and my Drawing Number Two.<br/>Grown-ups never understand anything by themselves, and it is tiresome for children to be always and forever explaining things to them.<br/>So then I chose another profession, and learned to pilot air-planes.<br/>I have flown a little over all parts of the world; and it is true that geography has been very useful to me.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On disait dans le livre : ' Les serpents boas avalent leur proie tout entière, sans la mâcher.<br/>Ensuite ils ne peuvent plus bouger et ils dorment pendant les six mois de leur digestion.<br/>'<br/>J’ai alors beaucoup réfléchi sur les aventures de la jungle et, à mon tour, j’ai réussi, avec un crayon de couleur, à tracer mon premier dessin.<br/>Mon dessin numéro 1.<br/>Il était comme ça :<br/>J’ai montré mon chef-d’oeuvre aux grandes personnes et je leur ai demandé si mon dessin leur faisait peur.<br/>Elles m’ont répondu : ' Pourquoi un chapeau ferait-il peur ?<br/>'<br/>Mon dessin ne représentait pas un chapeau.<br/>Il représentait un serpent boa qui digérait un éléphant.<br/>J’ai alors dessiné l’intérieur du serpent boa, afin que les grandes personnes puissent comprendre.<br/>Elles ont toujours besoin d’explications.<br/>Mon dessin numéro 2 était comme ça :<br/>Les grandes personnes m’ont conseillé de laisser de côté les dessins de serpents boas ouverts ou fermés, et de m’intéresser plutôt à la géographie, à l’histoire, au calcul et à la grammaire.<br/>C’est ainsi que j’ai abandonné, à l’âge de six ans, une magnifique carrière de peintre.<br/>J’avais été découragé par l’insuccès de mon dessin numéro 1 et de mon dessin numéro 2.<br/>Les grandes personnes ne comprennent jamais rien toutes seules, et c’est fatigant, pour les enfants, de toujours et toujours leur donner des explications.<br/>J’ai donc dû choisir un autre métier et j’ai appris à piloter des avions.<br/>J’ai volé un peu partout dans le monde.<br/>Et la géographie, c’est exact, m’a beaucoup servi.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="8">
  <src xml:lang="EN">At a glance I can distinguish China from Arizona.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je savais reconnaître, du premier coup d’oeil, la Chine de l’Arizona.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="9">
  <src xml:lang="EN">If one gets lost in the night, such knowledge is valuable.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est très utile, si l’on est égaré pendant la nuit.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="10">
  <src xml:lang="EN">In the course of this life I have had a great many encounters with a great many people who have been concerned with matters of consequence.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai ainsi eu, au cours de ma vie, des tas de contacts avec des tas de gens sérieux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="11">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have lived a great deal among grown-ups.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai beaucoup vécu chez les grandes personnes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="12">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have seen them intimately, close at hand.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je les ai vues de très près.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="13">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And that hasn’t much improved my opinion of them.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça n’a pas trop amélioré mon opinion.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="14">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Whenever I met one of them who seemed to me at all clear-sighted, I tried the experiment of showing him my Drawing Number One, which I have always kept.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quand j’en rencontrais une qui me paraissait un peu lucide, je faisais l’expérience sur elle de mon dessin numéro 1 que j’ai toujours conservé.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="15">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I would try to find out, so, if this was a person of true understanding.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je voulais savoir si elle était vraiment compréhensive.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="16">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But, whoever it was, he, or she, would always say: "That is a hat.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais toujours elle me répondait : ' C’est un chapeau.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="17">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then I would never talk to that person about boa constrictors, or primeval forests, or stars.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' Alors je ne lui parlais ni de serpents boas, ni de forêts vierges, ni d’étoiles.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="18">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I would bring myself down to his level.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je me mettais à sa portée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="19">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I would talk to him about bridge, and golf, and politics, and neckties.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je lui parlais de bridge, de golf, de politique et de cravates.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="20">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And the grown-up would be greatly pleased to have met such a sensible man.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et la grande personne était bien contente de connaître un homme aussi raisonnable.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="21">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So I lived my life alone, without anyone that I could really talk to, until I had an accident with my plane in the Desert of Sahara, six years ago.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai ainsi vécu seul, sans personne avec qui parler véritablement, jusqu’à une panne dans le désert du Sahara, il y a six ans.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="22">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Something was broken in my engine.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quelque chose s’était cassé dans mon moteur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="23">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And as I had with me neither a mechanic nor any passengers, I set myself to attempt the difficult repairs all alone.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et comme je n’avais avec moi ni mécanicien, ni passagers, je me préparai à essayer de réussir, tout seul, une réparation difficile.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="24">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was a question of life or death for me: I had scarcely enough drinking water to last a week.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’était pour moi une question de vie ou de mort.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="25">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The first night, then, I went to sleep on the sand, a thousand miles from any human habitation.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’avais à peine de l’eau à boire pour huit jours.<br/>Le premier soir je me suis donc endormi sur le sable à mille milles de toute terre habitée.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="26">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I was more isolated than a shipwrecked sailor on a raft in the middle of the ocean.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’étais bien plus isolé qu’un naufragé sur un radeau au milieu de l’Océan.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-2" id="27">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Thus you can imagine my amazement, at sunrise, when I was awakened by an odd little voice.<br/>It said: "If you please, draw me a sheep!”<br/>"What!”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors vous imaginez ma surprise, au lever du jour, quand une drôle de petite voix m’a réveillé.<br/>Elle disait :<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="28">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Draw me a sheep!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– S’il vous plaît… dessine-moi un mouton !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-5" id="29">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I jumped to my feet, completely thunderstruck.<br/>I blinked my eyes hard.<br/>I looked carefully all around me.<br/>And I saw a most extraordinary small person, who stood there examining me with great seriousness.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Hein !<br/>– Dessine-moi un mouton… J’ai sauté sur mes pieds comme si j’avais été frappé par la foudre.<br/>J’ai bien frotté mes yeux.<br/>J’ai bien regardé.<br/>Et j’ai vu un petit bonhomme tout à fait extraordinaire qui me considérait gravement.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="30">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Here you may see the best portrait that, later, I was able to make of him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Voilà le meilleur portrait que, plus tard, j’ai réussi à faire de lui.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="31">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But my drawing is certainly very much less charming than its model.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais mon dessin, bien sûr, est beaucoup moins ravissant que le modèle.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="32">
  <src xml:lang="EN">That, however, is not my fault.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce n’est pas ma faute.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="33">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The grown-ups discouraged me in my painter’s career when I was six years old, and I never learned to draw anything, except boas from the outside and boas from the inside.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’avais été découragé dans ma carrière de peintre par les grandes personnes, à l’âge de six ans, et je n’avais rien appris à dessiner, sauf les boas fermés et les boas ouverts.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="34">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Now I stared at this sudden apparition with my eyes fairly starting out of my head in astonishment.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je regardai donc cette apparition avec des yeux tout ronds d’étonnement.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="35">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Remember, I had crashed in the desert a thousand miles from any inhabited region.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">N’oubliez pas que je me trouvais à mille milles de toute région habitée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="36">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And yet my little man seemed neither to be straying uncertainly among the sands, nor to be fainting from fatigue or hunger or thirst or fear.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Or mon petit bonhomme ne me semblait ni égaré, ni mort de fatigue, ni mort de faim, ni mort de soif, ni mort de peur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="37">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Nothing about him gave any suggestion of a child lost in the middle of the desert, a thousand miles from any human habitation.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il n’avait en rien l’apparence d’un enfant perdu au milieu du désert, à mille milles de toute région habitée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="38">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When at last I was able to speak, I said to him: "But, what are you doing here?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quand je réussis enfin à parler, je lui dis :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="39">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And in answer he repeated, very slowly, as if he were speaking of a matter of great consequence:</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais… qu’est-ce que tu fais là ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="40">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"If you please, draw me a sheep...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et il me répéta alors, tout doucement, comme une chose très sérieuse :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="41">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When a mystery is too overpowering, one dare not disobey.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– S’il vous plaît… dessine-moi un mouton… Quand le mystère est trop impressionnant, on n’ose pas désobéir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="42">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Absurd as it might seem to me, a thousand miles from any human habitation and in danger of death, I took out of my pocket a sheet of paper and my fountain pen.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Aussi absurde que cela me semblât à mille milles de tous les endroits habités et en danger de mort, je sortis de ma poche une feuille de papier et un stylographe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="43">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But then I remembered how my studies had been concentrated on geography, history, arithmetic, and grammar, and I told the little chap (a little crossly, too) that I did not know how to draw.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais je me rappelai alors que j’avais surtout étudié la géographie, l’histoire, le calcul et la grammaire et je dis au petit bonhomme (avec un peu de mauvaise humeur) que je ne savais pas dessiner.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="44">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He answered me: "That doesn’t matter.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me répondit :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="45">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Draw me a sheep...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça ne fait rien.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="46">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But I had never drawn a sheep.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Dessine-moi un mouton.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="47">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So I drew for him one of the two pictures I had drawn so often.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Comme je n’avais jamais dessiné un mouton je refis, pour lui, l’un des deux seuls dessins dont j’étais capable.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="48">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was that of the boa constrictor from the outside.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Celui du boa fermé.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="49">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And I was astounded to hear the little fellow greet it with, "No, no, no!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et je fus stupéfait d’entendre le petit bonhomme me répondre :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="50">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I do not want an elephant inside a boa constrictor.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Non ! Non ! Je ne veux pas d’un éléphant dans un boa.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="51">
  <src xml:lang="EN">A boa constrictor is a very dangerous creature, and an elephant is very cumbersome.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Un boa c’est très dangereux, et un éléphant c’est très encombrant.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="52">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Where I live, everything is very small.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Chez moi c’est tout petit.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="53">
  <src xml:lang="EN">What I need is a sheep.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai besoin d’un mouton.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="54">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Draw me a sheep.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Dessine- moi un mouton.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="55">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So then I made a drawing.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors j’ai dessiné.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="56">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He looked at it carefully, then he said: "No.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il regarda attentivement, puis :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="57">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This sheep is already very sickly.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Non ! Celui-là est déjà très malade.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="58">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Make me another.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Fais-en un autre.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="59">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So I made another drawing.<br/>My friend smiled gently and indulgently.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je dessinai : Mon ami sourit gentiment, avec indulgence :<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="60">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"You see yourself,” he said, "that this is not a sheep.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Tu vois bien… ce n’est pas un mouton, c’est un bélier.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-2" id="61">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This is a ram.<br/>It has horns.<br/>So then I did my drawing over once more.<br/>But it was rejected too, just like the others.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il a des cornes… Je refis donc encore mon dessin :<br/>Mais il fut refusé, comme les précédents :<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="62">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"This one is too old.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Celui-là est trop vieux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="63">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I want a sheep that will live a long time.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je veux un mouton qui vive longtemps.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="64">
  <src xml:lang="EN">By this time my patience was exhausted, because I was in a hurry to start taking my engine apart.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors, faute de patience, comme j’avais hâte de commencer le démontage de mon moteur, je griffonnai ce dessin-ci.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-3" id="65">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So I tossed off this drawing.<br/>And I threw out an explanation with it.<br/>"This is only his box.<br/>The sheep you asked for is inside.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et je lançai :<br/>– Ça c’est la caisse.<br/>Le mouton que tu veux est dedans.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="66">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I was very surprised to see a light break over the face of my young judge:</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais je fus bien surpris de voir s’illuminer le visage de mon jeune juge :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="67">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is exactly the way I wanted it!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est tout à fait comme ça que je le voulais !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="68">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Do you think that this sheep will have to have a great deal of</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Crois-tu qu’il faille beaucoup d’herbe à ce mouton ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="69">
  <src xml:lang="EN">grass?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Pourquoi ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="70">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Why?”<br/>"Because where I live everything is very small...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Parce que chez moi c’est tout petit…<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="71">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"There will surely be enough grass for him,” I said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça suffira sûrement.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="72">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is a very small sheep that I have given you.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je t’ai donné un tout petit mouton.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="73">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He bent his head over the drawing: "Not so small that, Look!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il pencha la tête vers le dessin :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="74">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He has gone to sleep...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Pas si petit que ça… Tiens !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="75">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And that is how I made the acquaintance of the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il s’est endormi… Et c’est ainsi que je fis la connaissance du petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="76">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It took me a long time to learn where he came from.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Voilà le meilleur portrait que, plus tard, j’ai réussi à faire de lui</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="77">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince, who asked me so many</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me fallut longtemps pour comprendre d’où il venait.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="78">
  <src xml:lang="EN">questions, never seemed to hear the ones I asked him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince, qui me posait beaucoup de questions, ne semblait jamais entendre les miennes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="79">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was from words dropped by chance that,</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce sont des mots prononcés par hasard qui, peu à peu, m’ont tout révélé.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="80">
  <src xml:lang="EN">little by little, everything was revealed to me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ainsi, quand il aperçut pour la première fois mon avion (je ne dessinerai pas mon avion, c’est un dessin beaucoup trop compliqué pour moi) il me demanda :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="81">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The first time he saw my air-plane, for instance (I shall not draw my air-plane; that would be much too complicated for me), he asked me: "What is that object?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Qu’est-ce que c’est que cette chose-là ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="82">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is not an object.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce n’est pas une chose.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="83">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It flies. It is an air-plane.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça vole. C’est un avion.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="84">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is my air-plane.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est mon avion.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="85">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And I was proud to have him learn that I could fly.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et j’étais fier de lui apprendre que je volais.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="86">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He cried out, then: "What!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors il s’écria :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="87">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You dropped down from the sky?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Comment ! tu es tombé du ciel ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="88">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes,” I answered, modestly.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Oui, fis-je modestement.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="89">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Oh! That is funny!”<br/>And the little prince broke into a lovely peal of laughter, which irritated me very much.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! ça c’est drôle… Et le petit prince eut un très joli éclat de rire qui m’irrita beaucoup.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="90">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I like my misfortunes to be taken seriously.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je désire que l’on prenne mes malheurs au sérieux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="7-9" id="91">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then he added: "So you, too, come from the sky!<br/>Which is your planet?”<br/>At that moment I caught a gleam of light in the impenetrable mystery of his presence; and I demanded, abruptly: "Do you come from another planet?”<br/>But he did not reply.<br/>He tossed his head gently, without taking his eyes from my plane: "It is true that on that you can’t have come from very far away...”<br/>And he sank into a reverie, which lasted a long time.<br/>Then, taking my sheep out of his pocket, he buried himself in the contemplation of his treasure.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Puis il ajouta :<br/>– Alors, toi aussi tu viens du ciel !<br/>De quelle planète es-tu ?<br/>J’entrevis aussitôt une lueur, dans le mystère de sa présence, et j’interrogeai brusquement :<br/>– Tu viens donc d’une autre planète ?<br/>Mais il ne me répondit pas.<br/>Il hochait la tête doucement tout en regardant mon avion :<br/>– C’est vrai que, là-dessus, tu ne peux pas venir de bien loin… Et il s’enfonça dans une rêverie qui dura longtemps.<br/>Puis, sortant mon mouton de sa poche, il se plongea dans la contemplation de son trésor.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="92">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You can imagine how my curiosity was aroused by this half-confidence about the "other planets.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vous imaginez combien j’avais pu être intrigué par cette demi-confidence sur ' les autres planètes '.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-6" id="93">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I made a great effort, therefore, to find out more on this subject.<br/>"My little man, where do you come from?<br/>What is this ‘where I live,’ of which you speak?<br/>Where do you want to take your sheep?”<br/>After a reflective silence he answered: "The thing that is so good about the box you have given me is that at night he can use it as his house.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je m’efforçai donc d’en savoir plus long :<br/>– D’où viens-tu, mon petit bonhomme ?<br/>Où est-ce ' chez toi ' ?<br/>Où veux-tu emporter mon mouton ?<br/>Il me répondit après un silence méditatif :<br/>– Ce qui est bien, avec la caisse que tu m’as donnée, c’est que, la nuit, ça lui servira de maison.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="94">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is so. And if you are good I will give you a string, too, so that you can tie him during the day, and a post to tie him to.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr. Et si tu es gentil, je te donnerai aussi une corde pour l’attacher pendant le jour.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="95">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But the little prince seemed shocked by this offer: "Tie him!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et un piquet. La proposition parut choquer le petit prince :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="10-12" id="96">
  <src xml:lang="EN">What a queer idea!”<br/>"But if you don’t tie him,” I said, "he will wander off somewhere, and get lost.”<br/>My friend broke into another peal of laughter: "But where do you think he would go?”<br/>"Anywhere. Straight ahead of him.”<br/>Then the little prince said, earnestly: "That doesn’t matter.<br/>Where I live, everything is so small!”<br/>And, with perhaps a hint of sadness, he added: "Straight ahead of him, nobody can go very far...”<br/>I had thus learned a second fact of great importance: this was that the planet the little prince came from was scarcely any larger than a house!<br/>But that did not really surprise me much.<br/>I knew very well that in addition to the great planets, such as the Earth, Jupiter, Mars, Venus, to which we have given names, there are also hundreds of others, some of which are so small that one has a hard time seeing them through the telescope.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– L’attacher ?<br/>Quelle drôle d’idée !<br/>– Mais si tu ne l’attaches pas, il ira n’importe où, et il se perdra… Et mon ami eut un nouvel éclat de rire :<br/>– Mais où veux-tu qu’il aille !<br/>– N’importe où.<br/>Droit devant lui… Alors le petit prince remarqua gravement :<br/>– Ça ne fait rien, c’est tellement petit, chez moi !<br/>Et, avec un peu de mélancolie, peut-être, il ajouta :<br/>– Droit devant soi on ne peut pas aller bien loin…<br/>J’avais ainsi appris une seconde chose très importante : C’est que sa planète d’origine était à peine plus grande qu’une maison !<br/>Ça ne pouvait pas m’étonner beaucoup.<br/>Je savais bien qu’en dehors des grosses planètes comme la Terre, Jupiter, Mars, Vénus, auxquelles on a donné des noms, il y en a des centaines d’autres qui sont quelquefois si petites qu’on a beaucoup de mal à les apercevoir au télescope.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="97">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When an astronomer discovers one of these he does not give it a name, but only a number.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quand un astronome découvre l’une d’elles, il lui donne pour nom un numéro.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="98">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He might call it, for example, "Asteroid 325.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il l’appelle par exemple : ' l’astéroïde 3251.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="99">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have serious reason to believe that the planet from which the little prince came is the asteroid known as B-612.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">'</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="100">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This asteroid has only once been seen through the telescope.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai de sérieuses raisons de croire que la planète d’où venait le petit prince est l’astéroïde B 612.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="101">
  <src xml:lang="EN">That was by a Turkish astronomer, in 1909.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cet astéroïde n’a été aperçu qu’une fois au télescope, en 1909, par un astronome turc.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="102">
  <src xml:lang="EN">On making his discovery, the astronomer had presented it to the International Astronomical Congress, in a great demonstration.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il avait fait alors une grande démonstration de sa découverte à un Congrès International d’Astronomie.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="103">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he was in Turkish costume, and so nobody would believe what he said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais personne ne l’avait cru à cause de son costume.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="104">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Grown-ups are like that...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les grandes personnes sont comme ça.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="105">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Fortunately, however, for the reputation of Asteroid B-612, a Turkish dictator made a law that his subjects, under pain of death, should change to European costume.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Heureusement pour la réputation de l’astéroïde B 612 un dictateur turc imposa à son peuple, sous peine de mort, de s’habiller à l’Européenne.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="106">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So in 1920 the astronomer gave his demonstration all over again, dressed with impressive style and elegance.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">L’astronome refit sa démonstration en 1920, dans un habit très élégant.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-5" id="107">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And this time everybody accepted his report.<br/>If I have told you these details about the asteroid, and made a note of its number for you, it is on account of the grown-ups and their ways.<br/>When you tell them that you have made a new friend, they never ask you any questions about essential matters.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et cette fois-ci tout le monde fut de son avis.<br/>Si je vous ai raconté ces détails sur l’astéroïde B 612 et si je vous ai confié son numéro, c’est à cause des grandes personnes.<br/>Les grandes personnes aiment les chiffres.<br/>Quand vous leur par<br/>lez d’un nouvel ami, elles ne vous questionnent jamais sur l’essentiel.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="108">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They never say to you, "What does his voice sound like?</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles ne vous disent jamais : ' Quel est le son de sa voix ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="109">
  <src xml:lang="EN">What games does he love best?</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quels sont les jeux qu’il préfère ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="13-12" id="110">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Does he collect butterflies?”<br/>Instead, they demand: "How old is he?<br/>How many brothers has he?<br/>How much does he weigh?<br/>How much money does his father make?”<br/>Only from these figures do they think they have learned anything about him.<br/>If you were to say to the grown-ups: "I saw a beautiful house made of rosy brick, with geraniums in the windows and doves on the roof,” they would not be able to get any idea of that house at all.<br/>You would have to say to them: "I saw a house that cost $ 20,000.”<br/>Then they would exclaim: "Oh, what a pretty house that is!”<br/>Just so, you might say to them: "The proof that the little prince existed is that he was charming, that he laughed, and that he was looking for a sheep.<br/>If anybody wants a sheep, that is a proof that he exists.”<br/>And what good would it do to tell them that?<br/>They would shrug their shoulders, and treat you like a child.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Est-ce qu’il collectionne les papillons ?<br/>' Elles vous demandent : ' Quel âge a-t-il ?<br/>Combien a-t-il de frères ?<br/>Combien pèse-t-il ?<br/>Combien gagne son père ?<br/>' Alors seulement elles croient le connaître.<br/>Si vous dites aux grandes personnes : ' J’ai vu une belle maison en briques roses, avec des géraniums aux fenêtres et des colombes sur le toit… ' elles ne parviennent pas à s’imaginer cette maison.<br/>Il faut leur dire : ' J’ai vu une maison de cent mille francs.<br/>' Alors elles s’écrient : ' Comme c’est joli !<br/>'<br/>Ainsi, si vous leur dites : ' La preuve que le petit prince a existé c’est qu’il était ravissant, qu’il riait, et qu’il voulait un mouton.<br/>Quand on veut un mouton, c’est la preuve qu’on existe ' elles hausseront les épaules et vous traiteront d’enfant !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="111">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But if you said to them: "The planet he came from is Asteroid B-612,” then they would be convinced, and leave you in peace from their questions.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais si vous leur dites : ' La planète d’où il venait est l’astéroïde B 612 ' alors elles seront convaincues, et elles vous laisseront tranquille avec leurs questions.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="112">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They are like that.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles sont comme ça.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="113">
  <src xml:lang="EN">One must not hold it against them.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il ne faut pas leur en vouloir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="114">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Children should always show great forbearance toward grown-up people.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les enfants doivent être très indulgents envers les grandes personnes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="115">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But certainly, for us who understand life, figures are a matter of indifference.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais, bien sûr, nous qui comprenons la vie, nous nous moquons bien des numéros !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="7-6" id="116">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I should have liked to begin this story in the fashion of the fairy-tales.<br/>I should have like to say: "Once upon a time there was a little prince who lived on a planet that was scarcely any bigger<br/>than himself, and who had need of a sheep...”<br/>To those who understand life, that would have given a much greater air of truth to my story.<br/>For I do not want any one to read my book carelessly.<br/>I have suffered too much grief in setting down these memories.<br/>Six years have already passed since my friend went away from me, with his sheep.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’aurais aimé commencer cette histoire à la façon des contes de fées.<br/>J’aurais aimé dire :<br/>' Il était une fois un petit prince qui habitait une planète à peine plus grande que lui, et qui avait besoin d’un ami… ' Pour ceux qui comprennent la vie, ça aurait eu l’air beaucoup plus vrai.<br/>Car je n’aime pas qu’on lise mon livre à la légère.<br/>J’éprouve tant de chagrin à raconter ces souvenirs.<br/>Il y a six ans déjà que mon ami s’en est allé avec son mouton.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="117">
  <src xml:lang="EN">If I try to describe him here, it is to make sure that I shall not forget him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Si j’essaie ici de le décrire, c’est afin de ne pas l’oublier.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="118">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To forget a friend is sad.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est triste d’oublier un ami.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-3" id="119">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Not every one has had a friend.<br/>And if I forget him, I may become like the grown-ups who are no longer interested in anything but figures...<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tout le monde n’a pas eu un ami.<br/>Et je puis devenir comme les<br/>grandes personnes qui ne s’intéressent plus qu’aux chiffres.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="120">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is for that purpose, again, that I have bought a box of paints and some pencils.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est donc pour ça encore que j’ai acheté une boîte de couleurs et des crayons.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="121">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is hard to take up drawing again at my age, when I have never made any pictures except those of the boa constrictor from the outside and the boa constrictor from the inside, since I was six.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est dur de se remettre au dessin, à mon âge, quand on n’a jamais fait d’autres tentatives que celle d’un boa fermé et celle d’un boa ouvert, à l’âge de six ans !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="122">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I shall certainly try to make my portraits as true to life as possible.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’essaierai, bien sûr, de faire des portraits le plus ressemblants possible.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="123">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But I am not at all sure of success.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais je ne suis pas tout à fait certain de réussir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="124">
  <src xml:lang="EN">One drawing goes along all right, and another has no resemblance to its subject.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Un dessin va, et l’autre ne ressemble plus.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="8-10" id="125">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I make some errors, too, in the little prince’s height: in one place he is too tall and in another too short.<br/>And I feel some doubts about the colour of his costume.<br/>So I fumble along as best I can, now good, now bad, and I hope generally fair-to-middling.<br/>In certain more important details I shall make mistakes, also.<br/>But that is something that will not be my fault.<br/>My friend never explained anything to me.<br/>He thought, perhaps, that I was like himself.<br/>But I, alas, do not know how to see sheep through the walls of boxes.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je me trompe un peu aussi sur la taille.<br/>Ici le petit prince est trop grand.<br/>Là il est trop petit.<br/>J’hésite aussi sur la couleur de son costume.<br/>Alors je tâtonne comme ci et comme ça, tant bien que mal.<br/>Je me tromperai enfin sur certains détails plus importants.<br/>Mais ça, il faudra me le pardonner.<br/>Mon ami ne donnait jamais d’explications.<br/>Il me croyait peut-être semblable à lui.<br/>Mais moi, malheureusement, je ne sais pas voir les moutons à travers les caisses.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="126">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Perhaps I am a little like the grown-ups.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je suis peut- être un peu comme les grandes personnes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="127">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have had to grow old.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai dû vieillir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="128">
  <src xml:lang="EN">As each day passed I would learn, in our talk, something about the little prince’s planet, his departure from it, his journey.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Chaque jour j’apprenais quelque chose sur la planète, sur le départ, sur le voyage.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="129">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The information would come very slowly, as it might chance to fall from his thoughts.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça venait tout doucement, au hasard des réflexions.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="130">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was in this way that I heard, on the third day, about the catastrophe of the baobabs.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est ainsi que, le troisième jour, je connus le drame des baobabs.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="131">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This time, once more, I had the sheep to thank for it.<br/>For the little prince asked me abruptly, as if seized by a grave doubt,<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cette fois-ci encore ce fut grâce au mouton, car brusquement le petit prince m’interrogea, comme pris d’un doute grave :<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="132">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is true, isn’t it, that sheep eat little bushes?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est bien vrai, n’est-ce pas, que les moutons mangent les arbustes ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="133">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, that is true.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Oui. C’est vrai.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-4" id="134">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah! I am glad!”<br/>I did not understand why it was so important that sheep should eat little bushes.<br/>But the little prince added: "Then it follows that they also eat baobabs?”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! Je suis content.<br/>Je ne compris pas pourquoi il était si important que les moutons mangeassent les arbustes.<br/>Mais le petit prince ajouta :<br/>– Par conséquent ils mangent aussi les baobabs ?<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="135">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I pointed out to the little prince that baobabs were not little bushes, but, on the contrary, trees as big as castles; and that even if he took a whole herd of elephants away with him, the herd would not eat up one single baobab.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je fis remarquer au petit prince que les baobabs ne sont pas des arbustes, mais des arbres grands comme des églises et que, si même il emportait avec lui tout un troupeau d’éléphants, ce troupeau ne viendrait pas à bout d’un seul baobab.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="136">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The idea of the herd of elephants made the little prince laugh.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">L’idée du troupeau d’éléphants fit rire le petit prince :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="137">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"We would have to put them one on top of the other,” he said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Il faudrait les mettre les uns sur les autres…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="138">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he made a wise comment:</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais il remarqua avec sagesse :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="139">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Before they grow so big, the baobabs start out by being little.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Les baobabs, avant de grandir, ça commence par être petit.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="140">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is strictly correct,” I said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est exact !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="141">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But why do you want the sheep to eat the little baobabs?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais pourquoi veux-tu que tes moutons mangent les petits baobabs ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-3" id="142">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He answered me at once, "Oh, come, come!”, as if he were speaking of something that was selfevident.<br/>And I was obliged to make a great mental effort to solve this problem, without any assistance.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me répondit : ' Ben !<br/>Voyons ! ' comme s’il s’agissait là d’une évidence.<br/>Et il me fallut un grand effort d’intelligence pour comprendre à moi seul ce problème.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="143">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Indeed, as I learned, there were on the planet where the little prince lived, as on all planets, good</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et en effet, sur la planète du petit prince, il y avait comme sur toutes les planètes, de bonnes herbes et de mauvaises herbes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="144">
  <src xml:lang="EN">plants and bad plants.<br/>In consequence, there were good seeds from good plants, and bad seeds from bad plants.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Par conséquent de bonnes graines de bonnes herbes et de mauvaises graines de mauvaises herbes.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="145">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But seeds are invisible.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais les graines sont invisibles.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-5" id="146">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They sleep deep in the heart of the earth’s darkness, until some one among them is seized with the desire to awaken.<br/>Then this little seed will stretch itself and begin, timidly at first, to push a charming little sprig inoffensively upward toward the sun.<br/>If it is only a sprout of radish or the sprig of a rose-bush, one would let it grow wherever it might wish.<br/>But when it is a bad plant, one must destroy it as soon as possible, the very first instant that one recognises it.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles dorment dans le secret de la terre jusqu’à ce qu’il prenne fantaisie à l’une d’elles de se réveiller.<br/>Alors elle s’étire, et pousse d’abord timidement vers le soleil une ravissante petite brindille inoffensive.<br/>S’il s’agit d’une brindille de<br/>radis ou de rosier, on peut la laisser pousser comme elle veut.<br/>Mais s’il s’agit d’une mauvaise plante, il faut arracher la plante aussitôt, dès qu’on a su la reconnaître.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="147">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Now there were some terrible seeds on the planet that was the home of the little prince; and these were the seeds of the baobab.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Or il y avait des graines terribles sur la planète du petit prince… c’étaient les graines de baobabs.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="148">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The soil of that planet was infested with them.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le sol de la planète en était infesté.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="149">
  <src xml:lang="EN">A baobab is something you will never, never be able to get rid of if you attend to it too late.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Or un baobab, si l’on s’y prend trop tard, on ne peut jamais plus s’en débarrasser.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="150">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It spreads over the entire planet.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il encombre toute la planète.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="151">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It bores clear through it with its roots.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il la perfore de ses racines.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="152">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And if the planet is too small, and the baobabs are too many, they split it in pieces...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et si la planète est trop petite, et si les baobabs sont trop nombreux, ils la font éclater.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="153">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is a question of discipline,” the little prince said to me later on.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' C’est une question de discipline, me disait plus tard le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="154">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"When you’ve finished your own toilet in the morning, then it is time to attend to the toilet of your planet, just so, with the greatest care.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quand on a terminé sa toilette du matin, il faut faire soigneusement la toilette de la planète.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="155">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You must see to it that you pull up regularly all the baobabs, at the very first moment when they can be distinguished from the rosebushes, which they resemble so closely in their earliest youth.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il faut s’astreindre régulièrement à arracher les baobabs dès qu’on les distingue d’avec les rosiers auxquels ils ressemblent beaucoup quand ils sont très jeunes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-4" id="156">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is very tedious work,” the little prince added, "but very easy.”<br/>And one day he said to me: "You ought to make a beautiful drawing, so that the children where you live can see exactly how all this is.<br/>That would be very useful to them if they were to travel some day.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est un travail très ennuyeux, mais très facile.<br/>'<br/>Et un jour il me conseilla de m’appliquer à réussir un beau dessin, pour bien faire entrer ça dans la tête des enfants de chez moi.<br/>' S’ils voyagent un jour, me disait-il, ça pourra leur servir.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="157">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Sometimes,” he added, "there is no harm in putting off a piece of work until another day.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il est quelquefois sans inconvénient de remettre à plus tard son travail.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="158">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But when it is a matter of baobabs, that always means a catastrophe.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais, s’il s’agit des baobabs, c’est toujours une catastrophe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="159">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I knew a planet that was inhabited by a lazy man.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai connu une planète, habitée par un paresseux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="160">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He neglected three little bushes...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il avait négligé trois arbustes… '</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="161">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So, as the little prince described it to me, I have made a drawing of that planet.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et, sur les indications du petit prince, j’ai dessiné cette planète- là.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="162">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I do not much like to take the tone of a moralist.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je n’aime guère prendre le ton d’un moraliste.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="163">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But the danger of the baobabs is so little understood, and such considerable risks would be run by anyone who might get lost on an asteroid, that for once I am breaking through my reserve.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais le danger des baobabs est si peu connu, et les risques courus par celui qui s’égarerait dans un astéroïde sont si considérables, que, pour une fois, je fais exception à ma réserve.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="164">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Children,” I say plainly, "watch out for the baobabs!”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je dis : ' Enfants !<br/>Faites attention aux baobabs !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="165">
  <src xml:lang="EN">My friends, like myself, have been skirting this danger for a long time, without ever knowing it; and so it is for them that I have worked so hard over this drawing.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' C’est pour avertir mes amis d’un danger qu’ils frôlaient depuis longtemps, comme moi-même, sans le connaître, que j’ai tant travaillé ce dessin-là.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="166">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The lesson which I pass on by this means is worth all the trouble it has cost me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La leçon que je donnais en valait la peine.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="6-4" id="167">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Perhaps you will ask me, "Why are there no other drawing in this book as magnificent and impressive as this drawing of the baobabs?”<br/>The reply is simple.<br/>I have tried. But with the others I have not been successful.<br/>When I made the drawing of the baobabs I was carried beyond myself by the inspiring force of urgent necessity.<br/>Oh, little prince!<br/>Bit by bit I came to understand the secrets of your sad little life...<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vous vous demanderez peut-être : Pourquoi n’y a-t-il pas, dans ce livre, d’autres dessins aussi grandioses que le dessin des baobabs ?<br/>La réponse est bien simple : J’ai essayé mais je n’ai pas pu réussir.<br/>Quand j’ai dessiné les baobabs j’ai été animé par le sentiment de l’urgence.<br/>Ah ! petit prince, j’ai compris, peu à peu, ainsi, ta petite vie mélancolique.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="168">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For a long time you had found your only entertainment in the quiet pleasure of looking at the sunset.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu n’avais eu longtemps pour distraction que la douceur des couchers de soleil.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="169">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I learned that new detail on the morning of the fourth day, when you said to me:</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai appris ce détail nouveau, le quatrième jour au matin, quand tu m’as dit :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="11-10" id="170">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I am very fond of sunsets.<br/>Come, let us go look at a sunset now.”<br/>"But we must wait,” I said.<br/>"Wait? For what?”<br/>"For the sunset.<br/>We must wait until it is time.”<br/>At first you seemed to be very much surprised.<br/>And then you laughed to yourself.<br/>You said to me: "I am always thinking that I am at home!”<br/>Just so. Everybody knows that when it is noon in the United States the sun is setting over France.<br/>If you could fly to France in one minute, you could go straight into the sunset, right from noon.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– J’aime bien les couchers de soleil.<br/>Allons voir un coucher de soleil…<br/>– Mais il faut attendre…<br/>– Attendre quoi ?<br/>– Attendre que le soleil se couche.<br/>Tu as eu l’air très surpris d’abord, et puis tu as ri de toi- même.<br/>Et tu m’as dit :<br/>– Je me crois toujours chez moi !<br/>En effet. Quand il est midi aux États-Unis, le soleil, tout le monde le sait, se couche sur la France.<br/>Il suffirait de pouvoir aller en France en une minute pour assister au coucher de soleil.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="171">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Unfortunately, France is too far away for that.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Malheureusement la France est bien trop éloignée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="172">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But on your tiny planet, my little prince, all you need do is move your chair a few steps.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais, sur ta si petite planète, il te suffisait de tirer ta chaise de quelques pas.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="173">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You can see the day end and the twilight falling whenever you like...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et tu regardais le crépuscule chaque fois que tu le désirais…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="174">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"One day,” you said to me, "I saw the sunset forty-four times!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Un jour, j’ai vu le soleil se coucher quarante-trois fois !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="175">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And a little later you added: "You know, one loves the sunset, when one is so sad...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et un peu plus tard tu ajoutais :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="176">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Were you so sad, then?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Tu sais… quand on est tellement triste on aime les couchers de soleil…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="177">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I asked, "on the day of the forty-four sunsets?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Le jour des quarante-trois fois tu étais donc tellement triste ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="178">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But the little prince made no reply.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais le petit prince ne répondit pas.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="179">
  <src xml:lang="EN">On the fifth day, again, as always, it was thanks to the sheep, the secret of the little prince’s life was revealed to me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le cinquième jour, toujours grâce au mouton, ce secret de la vie du petit prince me fut révélé.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="180">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Abruptly, without anything to lead up to it, and as if the question had been born of long and silent meditation on his problem, he demanded: "A sheep; if it eats little bushes, does it eat flowers, too?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me demanda avec brusquerie, sans préambule, comme le fruit d’un problème longtemps médité en silence :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="181">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"A sheep,” I answered, "eats anything it finds in its reach.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Un mouton, s’il mange les arbustes, il mange aussi les fleurs ?<br/>– Un mouton mange tout ce qu’il rencontre.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="182">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Even flowers that have thorns?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Même les fleurs qui ont des épines ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="183">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, even flowers that have thorns.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Oui. Même les fleurs qui ont des épines.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="64-57" id="184">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Then the thorns, what use are they?”<br/>I did not know.<br/>At that moment I was very busy trying to unscrew a bolt that had got stuck in my engine.<br/>I was<br/>very much worried, for it was becoming clear to me that the breakdown of my plane was extremely serious.<br/>And I had so little drinking water left that I had to fear for the worst.<br/>"The thorns, what use are they?”<br/>The little prince never let go of a question, once he had asked it.<br/>As for me, I was upset over that bolt.<br/>And I answered with the first thing that came into my head: "The thorns are of no use at all.<br/>Flowers have thorns just for spite!”<br/>"Oh!” There was a moment of complete silence.<br/>Then the little prince flashed back at me, with a kind of resentfulness: "I don’t believe you!<br/>Flowers are weak creatures.<br/>They are naïve.<br/>They reassure themselves as best they can.<br/>They believe that their thorns are terrible weapons...”<br/>I did not answer.<br/>At that instant I was saying to myself: "If this bolt still won’t turn, I am going to<br/>knock it out with the hammer.”<br/>Again the little prince disturbed my thoughts.<br/>"And you actually believe that the flowers...”<br/>"Oh, no!” I cried. "No, no no! I don’t believe anything.<br/>I answered you with the first thing that<br/>came into my head.<br/>Don’t you see, I am very busy with matters of consequence!”<br/>He stared at me, thunderstruck.<br/>"Matters of consequence!”<br/>He looked at me there, with my hammer in my hand, my fingers black with engine grease, bending<br/>down over an object which seemed to him extremely ugly...<br/>"You talk just like the grown-ups!”<br/>That made me a little ashamed.<br/>But he went on, relentlessly: "You mix everything up together...<br/>You confuse everything...”<br/>He was really very angry.<br/>He tossed his golden curls in the breeze.<br/>"I know a planet where there is a certain red-faced gentleman.<br/>He has never smelled a flower.<br/>He<br/>has never looked at a star.<br/>He has never loved any one.<br/>He has never done anything in his life but add up figures.<br/>And all day he says over and over, just like you: ‘I am busy with matters of consequence!’<br/>And that makes him swell up with pride.<br/>"But he is not a man, he is a mushroom!”<br/>"A what?” "A mushroom!” The little prince was now white with rage.<br/>"The flowers have been growing thorns<br/>for millions of years.<br/>For millions of years the sheep have been eating them just the same.<br/>And is it not a matter of consequence to try to understand why the flowers go to so much trouble to grow<br/>thorns, which are never of any use to them?<br/>Is the warfare between the sheep and the flowers not important?<br/>Is this not of more consequence than a fat red-faced gentleman’s sums?<br/>And if I know, I, myself, one flower which is unique in the world, which grows nowhere but on my planet, but which one little sheep can destroy in a single bite some morning, without even noticing what he is doing, Oh!<br/>You think that is not important!<br/>His face turned from white to red as he continued: "If some one loves a flower, of which just one single blossom grows in all the millions and millions of stars, it is enough to make him happy just to look at the stars.<br/>He can say to himself, ‘Somewhere, my flower is there...’<br/>But if the sheep eats the flower, in one moment all his stars will be darkened...<br/>And you think that is not important!”<br/>He could not say anything more.<br/>His words were choked by sobbing.<br/>The night had fallen.<br/>I had let my tools drop from my hands.<br/>Of what moment now was my hammer, my bolt, or thirst, or death?<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Alors les épines, à quoi servent-elles ?<br/>Je ne le savais pas.<br/>J’étais alors très occupé à essayer de dévisser un boulon trop serré de mon moteur.<br/>J’étais très soucieux car ma panne commençait de m’apparaître comme très grave, et l’eau à boire qui s’épuisait me faisait craindre le pire.<br/>– Les épines, à quoi servent-elles ?<br/>Le petit prince ne renonçait jamais à une question, une fois qu’il l’avait posée.<br/>J’étais irrité par mon boulon et je répondis n’importe quoi :<br/>– Les épines, ça ne sert à rien, c’est de la pure méchanceté de la part des fleurs !<br/>– Oh ! Mais après un silence il me lança, avec une sorte de rancune :<br/>– Je ne te crois pas !<br/>Les fleurs sont faibles.<br/>Elles sont naïves.<br/>Elles se rassurent comme elles peuvent.<br/>Elles se croient terribles avec leurs épines… Je ne répondis rien.<br/>À cet instant-là je me disais : ' Si ce boulon résiste encore, je le ferai sauter d’un coup de marteau.<br/>' Le petit prince dérangea de nouveau mes réflexions :<br/>– Et tu crois, toi, que les fleurs…<br/>– Mais non ! Mais non ! Je ne crois rien !<br/>J’ai répondu n’importe quoi.<br/>Je m’occupe, moi, de choses sérieuses !<br/>Il me regarda stupéfait.<br/>– De choses sérieuses !<br/>Il me voyait, mon marteau à la main, et les doigts noirs de cambouis, penché sur un objet qui lui semblait très laid.<br/>– Tu parles comme les grandes personnes !<br/>Ça me fit un peu honte.<br/>Mais, impitoyable, il ajouta :<br/>– Tu confonds tout… tu mélanges tout !<br/>Il était vraiment très irrité.<br/>Il secouait au vent des cheveux tout dorés :<br/>– Je connais une planète où il y a un Monsieur cramoisi.<br/>Il n’a jamais respiré une fleur.<br/>Il n’a jamais regardé une étoile.<br/>Il n’a jamais aimé personne.<br/>Il n’a jamais rien fait d’autre que des additions.<br/>Et toute la journée il répète comme toi : ' Je suis un homme sérieux !<br/>Je suis un homme sérieux !<br/>' et ça le fait gonfler d’orgueil.<br/>Mais ce n’est pas un homme, c’est un champignon !<br/>– Un quoi ?<br/>– Un champignon !<br/>Le petit prince était maintenant tout pâle de colère.<br/>– Il y a des millions d’années que les fleurs fabriquent des épines.<br/>Il y a des millions d’années que les moutons mangent quand même les fleurs.<br/>Et ce n’est pas sérieux de chercher à comprendre pourquoi elles se donnent tant de mal pour se fabriquer des épines qui ne servent jamais à rien ?<br/>Ce n’est pas important la guerre des moutons et des fleurs ?<br/>Ce n’est pas plus sérieux et plus important que les additions d’un gros Monsieur rouge ?<br/>Et si je connais, moi, une fleur unique au monde, qui n’existe nulle part, sauf dans ma planète, et qu’un petit mouton peut anéantir d’un seul coup, comme ça, un matin, sans se rendre compte de ce qu’il fait, ce n’est pas important ça !<br/>Il rougit, puis reprit :<br/>– Si quelqu’un aime une fleur qui n’existe qu’à un exemplaire dans les millions et les millions d’étoiles, ça suffit pour qu’il soit heureux quand il les regarde.<br/>Il se dit : ' Ma fleur est là quelque part… ' Mais si le mouton mange la fleur, c’est pour lui comme si, brusquement, toutes les étoiles s’éteignaient !<br/>Et ce n’est pas important ça !<br/>– 30 –<br/>Il ne put rien dire de plus.<br/>Il éclata brusquement en sanglots.<br/>La nuit était tombée.<br/>J’avais lâché mes outils.<br/>Je me moquais bien de mon marteau, de mon boulon, de la soif et de la mort.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="185">
  <src xml:lang="EN">On one star, one planet, my planet, the Earth, there was a little prince to be comforted.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il y avait, sur une étoile, une planète, la mienne, la Terre, un petit prince à consoler !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="14-8" id="186">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I took him in my arms, and rocked him.<br/>I said to him: "The flower that you love is not in danger.<br/>I will draw you a muzzle for your sheep.<br/>I will draw you a railing to put around your flower.<br/>I will...”<br/>I did not know what to say to him.<br/>I felt awkward and blundering.<br/>I did not know how I could reach him, where I could overtake him and go on hand in hand with him once more.<br/>It is such a secret place, the land of tears.<br/>I soon learned to know this flower better.<br/>On the little prince’s planet the flowers had always been very simple.<br/>They had only one ring of petals; they took up no room at all; they were a trouble to nobody.<br/>One morning they would appear in the grass, and by night they would have faded peacefully away.<br/>But one day, from a seed blown from no one knew where, a new flower had come up; and the little prince had watched very closely over this small sprout which was not like any other small sprouts on his planet.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je le pris dans les bras.<br/>Je le berçai. Je lui disais : ' La fleur que tu aimes n’est pas en danger… Je lui dessinerai une muselière, à ton mouton… Je te dessinerai une armure pour ta fleur… Je… ' Je ne savais pas trop quoi dire.<br/>Je me sentais très maladroit.<br/>Je ne savais comment l’atteindre, où le rejoindre… C’est tellement mystérieux, le pays des larmes.<br/>J’appris bien vite à mieux connaître cette fleur.<br/>Il y avait toujours eu, sur la planète du petit prince, des fleurs très simples, ornées d’un seul rang de pétales, et qui ne tenaient point de place, et qui ne dérangeaient personne.<br/>Elles apparaissaient un matin dans l’herbe, et puis elles s’éteignaient le soir.<br/>Mais celle-là avait germé un jour, d’une graine apportée d’on ne sait où, et le petit prince avait surveillé de très près cette brindille qui ne ressemblait pas aux autres brindilles.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="187">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It might, you see, have been a new kind of baobab.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça pouvait être un nouveau genre de baobab.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="8-6" id="188">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The shrub soon stopped growing, and began to get ready to produce a flower.<br/>The little prince, who was present at the first appearance of a huge bud, felt at once that some sort of miraculous apparition must emerge from it.<br/>But the flower was not satisfied to complete the preparations for her beauty in the shelter of her green chamber.<br/>She<br/>chose her colours with the greatest care.<br/>She adjusted her petals one by one.<br/>She did not wish to go out into the world all rumpled, like the field poppies.<br/>It was only in the full radiance of her beauty that she wished to appear.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais l’arbuste cessa vite de croître, et commença de préparer une fleur.<br/>Le petit prince, qui assistait à l’installation d’un bouton énorme, sentait bien qu’il en sortirait une apparition miraculeuse, mais la fleur n’en finissait pas de se préparer à être belle, à l’abri de sa chambre verte.<br/>Elle choisissait avec soin ses couleurs.<br/>Elle s’habillait lentement, elle ajustait un à un ses pétales.<br/>Elle ne voulait pas sortir toute fripée comme les coquelicots.<br/>Elle ne voulait apparaître que dans le plein rayonnement de sa beauté.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="189">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Oh, yes! She was a coquettish creature!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Eh ! oui. Elle était très coquette !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="190">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And her mysterious adornment lasted for days and days.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Sa toilette mystérieuse avait donc duré des jours et des jours.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="191">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then one morning, exactly at sunrise, she suddenly showed herself.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et puis voici qu’un matin, justement à l’heure du lever du soleil, elle s’était montrée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="192">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And, after working with all this painstaking precision, she yawned and said: "Ah!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et elle, qui avait travaillé avec tant de précision, dit en bâillant :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="30-27" id="193">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I am scarcely awake.<br/>I beg that you will excuse me.<br/>My petals are still all disarranged...”<br/>But the little prince could not restrain his admiration:<br/>"Oh! How beautiful you are!”<br/>"Am I not?” the flower responded, sweetly.<br/>"And I was born at the same moment as the sun...”<br/>The little prince could guess easily enough that she was not any too modest, but how moving, and exciting she was!<br/>"I think it is time for breakfast,” she added an instant later.<br/>"If you would have the kindness to think of my needs” And the little prince, completely abashed, went to look for a sprinkling can of fresh water.<br/>So, he tended the flower.<br/>So, too, she began very quickly to torment him with her vanity, which was, if the truth be known, a little difficult to deal with.<br/>One day, for instance, when she was speaking of her four thorns, she said to the little prince: "Let the tigers come with their claws!”<br/>"There are no tigers on my planet,” the little prince objected.<br/>"And, anyway, tigers do not eat weeds.”<br/>"I am not a weed,” the flower replied, sweetly.<br/>"Please excuse me...”<br/>"I am not at all afraid of tigers,” she went on, "but I have a horror of drafts.<br/>I suppose you wouldn’t screen for me?"<br/>"A horror of drafts, that is bad luck, for a plant,” remarked the little prince, and added to himself, "This flower is a very complex creature...”<br/>"At night I want you to put me under a glass globe.<br/>It is very cold where you live.<br/>In the place I came from...”<br/>But she interrupted herself at that point.<br/>She had come in the form of a seed.<br/>She could not have known anything of any other worlds.<br/>Embarrassed over having let herself be caught on the verge of such an untruth, she coughed two or three times, in order to put the little prince in the wrong.<br/>"The screen?”<br/>"I was just going to look for it when you spoke to me...”<br/>Then she forced her cough a little more so that he should suffer from remorse just the same.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! Je me réveille à peine… Je vous demande pardon… Je suis encore toute décoiffée… Le petit prince, alors, ne put contenir son admiration :<br/>– Que vous êtes belle !<br/>– N’est-ce pas, répondit doucement la fleur.<br/>Et je suis née en même temps que le soleil… Le petit prince devina bien qu’elle n’était pas trop modeste, mais elle était si émouvante !<br/>– C’est l’heure, je crois, du petit déjeuner, avait-elle bientôt ajouté, auriez-vous la bonté de penser à moi… Et le petit prince, tout confus, ayant été chercher un arrosoir d’eau fraîche, avait servi la fleur.<br/>Ainsi l’avait-elle bien vite tourmenté par sa vanité un peu ombrageuse.<br/>Un jour, par exemple, parlant de ses quatre épines, elle avait dit au petit prince :<br/>– Ils peuvent venir, les tigres, avec leurs griffes !<br/>– Il n’y a pas de tigres sur ma planète, avait objecté le petit prince, et puis les tigres ne mangent pas l’herbe.<br/>– Je ne suis pas une herbe, avait doucement répondu la fleur.<br/>– Pardonnez-moi…<br/>– Je ne crains rien des tigres, mais j’ai horreur des courants d’air.<br/>Vous n’auriez pas un paravent ?<br/>' Horreur des courants d’air… ce n’est pas de chance, pour une plante, avait remarqué le petit prince.<br/>Cette fleur est bien compliquée… '<br/>– Le soir vous me mettrez sous globe.<br/>Il fait très froid chez vous.<br/>C’est mal installé.<br/>Là d’où je viens…<br/>Mais elle s’était interrompue.<br/>Elle était venue sous forme de graine.<br/>Elle n’avait rien pu connaître des autres mondes.<br/>Humiliée de s’être laissé surprendre à préparer un mensonge aussi naïf, elle avait toussé deux ou trois fois, pour mettre le petit prince dans son tort :<br/>– Ce paravent ?<br/>…<br/>– J’allais le chercher mais vous me parliez !<br/>Alors elle avait forcé sa toux pour lui infliger quand même des remords.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="194">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So the little prince, in spite of all the good will that was inseparable from his love, had soon come to doubt her.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ainsi le petit prince, malgré la bonne volonté de son amour, avait vite douté d’elle.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="195">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He had taken seriously words which were without importance, and it made him very unhappy.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il avait pris au sérieux des mots sans importance, et était devenu très malheureux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="196">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I ought not to have listened to her,” he confided to me one day.<br/>"One never ought to listen to the flowers.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' J’aurais dû ne pas l’écouter, me confia-t-il un jour, il ne faut jamais écouter les fleurs.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="197">
  <src xml:lang="EN">One should simply look at them and breathe their</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il faut les regarder et les respirer.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="198">
  <src xml:lang="EN">fragrance. Mine perfumed all my planet.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La mienne embaumait ma planète, mais je ne savais pas m’en réjouir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="199">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But I did not know how to take pleasure in all her grace.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cette histoire de griffes, qui m’avait tellement agacé, eût dû m’attendrir… '</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="200">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This tale of claws, which disturbed me so much, should only have filled my heart with tenderness and pity.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me confia encore :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="201">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he continued his confidences: "The fact is that I did not know how to understand anything!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' Je n’ai alors rien su comprendre !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="202">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I ought to have judged by deeds and not by words.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’aurais dû la juger sur les actes et non sur les mots.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="203">
  <src xml:lang="EN">She cast her fragrance and her radiance over me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elle m’embaumait et m’éclairait.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="204">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I ought never to have run away from her...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je n’aurais jamais dû m’enfuir !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="205">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I ought to have guessed all the affection that lay behind her poor little stratagems.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’aurais dû deviner sa tendresse derrière ses pauvres ruses.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="206">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Flowers are so inconsistent!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les fleurs sont si contradictoires !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="207">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But I was too young to know how to love her...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais j’étais trop jeune pour savoir l’aimer.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="208">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I believe that for his escape he took advantage of the migration of a flock of wild birds.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">'<br/>Je crois qu’il profita, pour son évasion, d’une migration d’oiseaux sauvages.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="209">
  <src xml:lang="EN">On the morning of his departure he put his planet in perfect order.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Au matin du départ il mit sa planète bien en ordre.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="210">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He carefully cleaned out his active volcanoes.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il ramona soigneusement ses volcans en activité.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="6-8" id="211">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He possessed two active volcanoes; and they were very convenient for heating his breakfast in the morning.<br/>He also had one volcano that was extinct.<br/>But, as he said, "One never knows!”<br/>So he cleaned out the extinct volcano, too.<br/>If they are well cleaned out, volcanoes burn slowly and steadily, without any eruptions.<br/>Volcanic eruptions are like fires in a chimney.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il pos<br/>sédait deux volcans en activité.<br/>Et c’était bien commode pour faire chauffer le petit déjeuner du matin.<br/>Il possédait aussi un volcan éteint.<br/>Mais, comme il disait, ' On ne sait jamais !<br/>' Il ramona donc également le volcan éteint.<br/>S’ils sont bien ramonés, les volcans brûlent doucement et régulièrement, sans éruptions.<br/>Les éruptions volcaniques sont comme des feux de cheminée.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="212">
  <src xml:lang="EN">On our earth we are obviously much too small to clean out our volcanoes.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Évidemment sur notre terre nous sommes beaucoup trop petits pour ramoner nos volcans.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="213">
  <src xml:lang="EN">That is why they bring no end of trouble upon us.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est pourquoi ils nous causent des tas d’ennuis.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="214">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince also pulled up, with a certain sense of dejection, the last little shoots of the baobabs.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince arracha aussi, avec un peu de mélancolie, les dernières pousses de baobabs.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="215">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He believed that he would never want to return.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il croyait ne jamais devoir revenir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="216">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But on this last morning all these familiar tasks seemed very precious to him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais tous ces travaux familiers lui parurent, ce matin- là, extrêmement doux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="217">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And when he watered the flower for the last time, and prepared to place her under the shelter of her glass globe, he realised that he was very close to tears.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et, quand il arrosa une dernière fois la fleur, et se prépara à la mettre à l’abri sous son globe, il se découvrit l’envie de pleurer.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="218">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Goodbye,” he said to the flower.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Adieu, dit-il à la fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="219">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But she made no answer.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais elle ne lui répondit pas.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="220">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Goodbye,” he said again.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Adieu, répéta-t-il.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="221">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The flower coughed.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La fleur toussa.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="222">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But it was not because she had a cold.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais ce n’était pas à cause de son rhume.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="223">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I have been silly,” she said to him, at last.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– J’ai été sotte, lui dit-elle enfin.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="224">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I ask your forgiveness.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je te demande pardon.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="225">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Try to be happy...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tâche d’être heureux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="226">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He was surprised by this absence of reproaches.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il fut surpris par l’absence de reproches.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="227">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He stood there all bewildered, the glass globe held arrested in mid-air.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il restait là tout déconcerté, le globe en l’air.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="228">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He did not understand this quiet sweetness.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il ne comprenait pas cette douceur calme.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="229">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Of course I love you,” the flower said to him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais oui, je t’aime, lui dit la fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="230">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is my fault that you have not known it all the while.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu n’en as rien su, par ma faute.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="231">
  <src xml:lang="EN">That is of no importance.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cela n’a aucune importance.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="232">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But you, you have been just as foolish as I.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais tu as été aussi sot que moi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="233">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Try to be happy... let the glass globe be.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tâche d’être heureux… Laisse ce globe tranquille.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="234">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I don’t want it any more.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je n’en veux plus.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="235">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But the wind...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais le vent…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="236">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"My cold is not so bad as all that... the cool night air will do me good.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je ne suis pas si enrhumée que ça… L’air frais de la nuit me fera du bien.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="237">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I am a flower.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je suis une fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="238">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But the animals...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais les bêtes…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="239">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Well, I must endure the presence of two or three caterpillars if I wish to become acquainted with the butterflies.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Il faut bien que je supporte deux ou trois chenilles si je veux connaître les papillons.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="12-13" id="240">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It seems that they are very beautiful.<br/>And if not the butterflies and the caterpillars who will call upon me?<br/>You will be far away... as for the large animals, I am not at all afraid of any of them.<br/>I have my claws.”<br/>And, naively, she showed her four thorns.<br/>Then she added: "Don’t linger like this.<br/>You have decided to go away.<br/>Now go!”<br/>For she did not want him to see her crying.<br/>She was such a proud flower...<br/>He found himself in the neighbourhood of the asteroids 325, 326, 327, 328, 329, and 330.<br/>He began, therefore, by visiting them, in order to add to his knowledge.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il paraît que c’est tellement beau.<br/>Sinon qui me rendra visite ?<br/>Tu seras loin, toi.<br/>Quant aux grosses bêtes, je ne crains rien.<br/>J’ai mes griffes.<br/>Et elle montrait naïvement ses quatre épines.<br/>Puis elle ajouta :<br/>– Ne traîne pas comme ça, c’est agaçant.<br/>Tu as décidé de partir.<br/>Va-t’en. Car elle ne voulait pas qu’il la vît pleurer.<br/>C’était une fleur tellement orgueilleuse…<br/>Il se trouvait dans la région des astéroïdes 325, 326, 327, 328, 329 et 330.<br/>Il commença donc par les visiter pour y chercher une occupation et pour s’instruire.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="241">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The first of them was inhabited by a king.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La première était habitée par un roi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-6" id="242">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Clad in royal purple and ermine, he was seated upon a throne, which was at<br/>the same time both simple and majestic.<br/>"Ah! Here is a subject,” exclaimed the king, when he saw the little prince coming.<br/>And the little prince asked himself: "How could he recognise me when he had never seen me before?”<br/>He did not know how the world is simplified for kings.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le roi siégeait, habillé de pourpre et d’hermine, sur un trône très simple et cependant majestueux.<br/>– Ah ! Voilà un sujet, s’écria le roi quand il aperçut le petit prince.<br/>Et le petit prince se demanda :<br/>' Comment peut-il me reconnaître puisqu’il ne m’a encore jamais vu !<br/>'<br/>Il ne savait pas que, pour les rois, le monde est très simplifié.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="243">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To them, all men are subjects.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tous les hommes sont des sujets.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="244">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Approach, so that I may see you better,” said the king, who felt consumingly proud of being at last a king over somebody.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Approche-toi que je te voie mieux, lui dit le roi qui était tout fier d’être roi pour quelqu’un.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="245">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince looked everywhere to find a place to sit down; but the entire planet was crammed and obstructed by the king’s magnificent ermine robe.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince chercha des yeux où s’asseoir, mais la planète était toute encombrée par le magnifique manteau d’hermine.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="246">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So he remained standing upright, and, since he was tired, he yawned.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il resta donc debout, et, comme il était fatigué, il bâilla.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="247">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is contrary to etiquette to yawn in the presence of a king,” the monarch said to him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Il est contraire à l’étiquette de bâiller en présence d’un roi, lui dit le monarque.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="248">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I forbid you to do so.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je te l’interdis.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="249">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I can’t help it.<br/>I can’t stop myself,” replied the little prince, thoroughly embarrassed.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je ne peux pas m’en empêcher, répondit le petit prince tout confus.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="250">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I have come on a long journey, and I have had no sleep...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai fait un long voyage et je n’ai pas dormi…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="251">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah, then,” the king said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Alors, lui dit le roi, je t’ordonne de bâiller.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="6-5" id="252">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I order you to yawn.<br/>It is years since I have seen anyone yawning.<br/>Yawns, to me, are objects of curiosity.<br/>Come, now! Yawn again! It is an order.”<br/>"That frightens me...<br/>I cannot, any more...” murmured the little prince, now completely abashed.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je n’ai vu personne bâiller depuis des années.<br/>Les bâillements sont pour moi des curiosités.<br/>Allons ! bâille encore.<br/>C’est un ordre.<br/>– Ça m’intimide… je ne peux plus… fit le petit prince tout rougissant.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="253">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Hum! Hum!” replied the king.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Hum ! Hum ! répondit le roi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="254">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Then I... I order you sometimes to yawn and sometimes to” He sputtered a little, and seemed vexed.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors je… je t’ordonne tantôt de bâiller et tantôt de… Il bredouillait un peu et paraissait vexé.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="255">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For what the king fundamentally insisted upon was that his authority should be respected.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Car le roi tenait essentiellement à ce que son autorité fût respectée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="256">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He tolerated no disobedience.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il ne tolérait pas la désobéissance.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="257">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He was an absolute monarch.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’était un monarque absolu.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="258">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But, because he was a very good man, he made his orders reasonable.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais, comme il était très bon, il donnait des ordres raisonnables.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="259">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"If I ordered a general,” he would say, by way of example, "if I ordered a general to change himself into a sea bird, and if the general did not obey me, that would not be the fault of the general.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' Si j’ordonnais, disait-il couramment, si j’ordonnais à un général de se changer en oiseau de mer, et si le général n’obéissait pas, ce ne serait pas la faute du général.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-5" id="260">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It would be my fault.”<br/>"May I sit down?”<br/>came now a timid inquiry from the little prince.<br/>"I order you to do so,” the king answered him, and majestically gathered in a fold of his ermine mantle.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce serait ma faute.<br/>'<br/>– Puis-je m’asseoir ?<br/>s’enquit timidement le petit prince.<br/>– Je t’ordonne de t’asseoir, lui répondit le roi, qui ramena majestueusement un pan de son manteau d’hermine.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="261">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But the little prince was wondering...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais le petit prince s’étonnait.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="262">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The planet was tiny.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La planète était minuscule.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="263">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Over what could this king really rule?</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Sur quoi le roi pouvait-il bien régner ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="264">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Sire,” he said to him, "I beg that you will excuse my asking you a question”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Sire, lui dit-il… je vous demande pardon de vous interroger…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="265">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I order you to ask me a question,” the king hastened to assure him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je t’ordonne de m’interroger, se hâta de dire le roi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="266">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Sire, over what do you rule?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Sire… sur quoi régnez-vous ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="267">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Over everything,” said the king, with magnificent simplicity.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Sur tout, répondit le roi, avec une grande simplicité.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-3" id="268">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Over everything?”<br/>The king made a gesture, which took in his planet, the other planets, and all the stars.<br/>"Over all that?”<br/>asked the little prince.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Sur tout ? Le roi d’un geste discret désigna sa planète, les autres planètes et les étoiles.<br/>– Sur tout ça ?<br/>dit le petit prince.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="269">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Over all that,” the king answered.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Sur tout ça… répondit le roi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="270">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For his rule was not only absolute: it was also universal.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Car non seulement c’était un monarque absolu mais c’était un monarque universel.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="271">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"And the stars obey you?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Et les étoiles vous obéissent ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="272">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Certainly they do,” the king said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr, lui dit le roi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="14-11" id="273">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"They obey instantly.<br/>I do not permit insubordination.”<br/>Such power was a thing for the little prince to marvel at.<br/>If he had been master of such complete authority, he would have been able to watch the sunset, not forty-four times in one day, but seventy-two, or even a hundred, or even two hundred times, with out ever having to move his chair.<br/>And because he felt a bit sad as he remembered his little planet, which he had forsaken, he plucked up his courage to ask the king a favour:<br/>"I should like to see a sunset... do me that kindness...<br/>Order the sun to set...”<br/>"If I ordered a general to fly from one flower to another like a butterfly, or to write a tragic drama, or to change himself into a sea bird, and if the general did not carry out the order that he had received, which one of us would be in the wrong?”<br/>the king demanded.<br/>"The general, or myself?”<br/>"You,” said the little prince firmly.<br/>"Exactly. One much require from each one the duty which each one can perform,” the king went on.<br/>"Accepted authority rests first of all on reason.<br/>If you ordered your people to go and throw themselves into the sea, they would rise up in revolution.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles obéissent aussitôt.<br/>Je ne tolère pas l’indiscipline.<br/>Un tel pouvoir émerveilla le petit prince.<br/>S’il l’avait détenu lui-même, il aurait pu assister, non pas à quarante-quatre, mais à soixante-douze, ou même à cent, ou même à deux cents couchers de soleil dans la même journée, sans avoir jamais à tirer sa chaise !<br/>Et comme il se sentait un peu triste à cause du souvenir de sa petite planète abandonnée, il s’enhardit à solliciter une grâce du roi :<br/>– Je voudrais voir un coucher de soleil… Faites-moi plaisir… Ordonnez au soleil de se coucher…<br/>– Si j’ordonnais à un général de voler d’une fleur à l’autre à la façon d’un papillon, ou d’écrire une tragédie, ou de se changer en oiseau de mer, et si le général n’exécutait pas l’ordre reçu, qui, de lui ou de moi, serait dans son tort ?<br/>– Ce serait vous, dit fermement le petit prince.<br/>– Exact. Il faut exiger de chacun ce que chacun peut donner, reprit le roi.<br/>L’autorité repose d’abord sur la raison.<br/>Si tu ordonnes à ton peuple d’aller se jeter à la mer, il fera la révolution.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="274">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have the right to require obedience because my orders are reasonable.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai le droit d’exiger l’obéissance parce que mes ordres sont raisonnables.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="275">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Then my sunset?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Alors mon coucher de soleil ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="276">
  <src xml:lang="EN">the little prince reminded him: for he never forgot a question once he had asked it.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">rappela le petit prince qui jamais n’oubliait une question une fois qu’il l’avait posée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="277">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"You shall have your sunset.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ton coucher de soleil, tu l’auras.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="278">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I shall command it.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je l’exigerai.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="279">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But, according to my science of government, I shall wait until conditions are favourable.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais j’attendrai, dans ma science du gouvernement, que les conditions soient favorables.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="280">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"When will that be?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Quand ça sera-t-il ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="281">
  <src xml:lang="EN">inquired the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">s’informa le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="282">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Hum! Hum!” replied the king; and before saying anything else he consulted a bulky almanac.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Hem ! hem ! lui répondit le roi, qui consulta d’abord un gros calendrier, hem !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="283">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Hum! Hum! That will be about... about... that will be this evening about twenty minutes to eight.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">hem ! ce sera, vers… vers… ce sera ce soir vers sept heures quarante !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="284">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And you will see how well I am obeyed.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et tu verras comme je suis bien obéi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="285">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince yawned.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince bâilla.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="286">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He was regretting his lost sunset.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il regrettait son coucher de soleil manqué.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="287">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And then, too, he was already beginning to be a little bored.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et puis il s’ennuyait déjà un peu :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="288">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I have nothing more to do here,” he said to the king.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je n’ai plus rien à faire ici, dit-il au roi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="289">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"So I shall set out on my way again.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je vais repartir !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="290">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Do not go,” said the king, who was very proud of having a subject.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ne pars pas, répondit le roi qui était si fier d’avoir un sujet.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="291">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Do not go. I will make you a Minister!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ne pars pas, je te fais ministre !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="292">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Minister of what?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ministre de quoi ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="293">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Minster of...of Justice!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– De… de la justice !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="294">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But there is nobody here to judge!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais il n’y a personne à juger !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="295">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"We do not know that,” the king said to him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– On ne sait pas, lui dit le roi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="296">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I have not yet made a complete tour of my kingdom.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je n’ai pas fait encore le tour de mon royaume.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="9-7" id="297">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I am very old.<br/>There is no room here for a carriage.<br/>And it tires me to walk.”<br/>"Oh, but I have looked already!”<br/>said the little prince, turning around to give one more glance to the other side of the planet.<br/>On that side, as on this, there was nobody at all...<br/>"Then you shall judge yourself,” the king answered. "that is the most difficult thing of all.<br/>It is much more difficult to judge oneself than to judge others.<br/>If you succeed in judging yourself rightly, then you are indeed a man of true wisdom.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je suis très vieux, je n’ai pas de place pour un carrosse, et ça me fatigue de marcher.<br/>– Oh ! Mais j’ai déjà vu, dit le petit prince qui se pencha pour jeter encore un coup d’oeil sur l’autre côté de la planète.<br/>Il n’y a personne là-bas non plus…<br/>– Tu te jugeras donc toi-même, lui répondit le roi.<br/>C’est le plus difficile.<br/>Il est bien plus difficile de se juger soi-même que de juger autrui.<br/>Si tu réussis à bien te juger, c’est que tu es un véritable sage.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="298">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes,” said the little prince, "but I can judge myself anywhere.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Moi, dit le petit prince, je puis me juger moi-même n’importe où.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="299">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I do not need to live on this planet.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je n’ai pas besoin d’habiter ici.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-4" id="300">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Hum! Hum!” said the king.<br/>"I have good reason to believe that somewhere on my planet there is an old rat.<br/>I hear him at night.<br/>You can judge this old rat.<br/>From time to time you will condemn him to death.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Hem ! Hem ! dit le roi, je crois bien que sur ma planète il y a quelque part un vieux rat.<br/>Je l’entends la nuit.<br/>Tu pourras juger ce vieux rat.<br/>Tu le condamneras à mort de temps en temps.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="301">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Thus his life will depend on your justice.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ainsi sa vie dépendra de ta justice.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-4" id="302">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But you will pardon him on each occasion; for he must be treated thriftily.<br/>He is the only one we have.”<br/>"I,” replied the little prince, "do not like to condemn anyone to death.<br/>And now I think I will go on my way.”<br/>"No,” said the king.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais tu le gracieras chaque fois pour l’économiser.<br/>Il n’y en a qu’un.<br/>– Moi, répondit le petit prince, je n’aime pas condamner à mort, et je crois bien que je m’en vais.<br/>– Non, dit le roi.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="303">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But the little prince, having now completed his preparations for departure, had no wish to grieve the old monarch.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais le petit prince, ayant achevé ses préparatifs, ne voulut point peiner le vieux monarque :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="304">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"If Your Majesty wishes to be promptly obeyed,” he said, "he should be able to give me a reasonable order.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Si Votre Majesté désirait être obéie ponctuellement, elle pourrait me donner un ordre raisonnable.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="305">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He should be able, for example, to order me to be gone by the end of one minute.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elle pourrait m’ordonner, par exemple, de partir avant une minute.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-2" id="306">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It seems to me that conditions are favourable...”<br/>As the king made no answer, the little prince hesitated a moment.<br/>Then, with a sigh, he took his leave.<br/>"I made you my Ambassador,” the king called out, hastily.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me semble que les conditions sont favorables… Le roi n’ayant rien répondu, le petit prince hésita d’abord, puis, avec un soupir, prit le départ.<br/>– Je te fais mon ambassadeur, se hâta alors de crier le roi.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="307">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He had a magnificent air of authority.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il avait un grand air d’autorité.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="308">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"The grown-ups are very strange,” the little prince said to himself, as he continued on his journey.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' Les grandes personnes sont bien étranges ', se dit le petit prince, en lui-même, durant son voyage.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="309">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The second planet was inhabited by a conceited man.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La seconde planète était habitée par un vaniteux :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="310">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah! Ah! I am about to receive a visit from an admirer!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! Ah ! Voilà la visite d’un admirateur !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="311">
  <src xml:lang="EN">he exclaimed from afar, when he first saw the little prince coming.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">s’écria de loin le vaniteux dès qu’il aperçut le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="312">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For, to conceited men, all other men are admirers.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Car, pour les vaniteux, les autres hommes sont des admirateurs.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="313">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="314">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is a queer hat you are wearing.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vous avez un drôle de chapeau.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="315">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is a hat for salutes,” the conceited man replied.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est pour saluer, lui répondit le vaniteux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="316">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is to raise in salute when people acclaim me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est pour saluer quand on m’acclame.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="317">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Unfortunately, nobody at all ever passes this way.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Malheureusement il ne passe jamais personne par ici.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="318">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes?” said the little prince, who did not understand what the conceited man was talking about.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah oui ? dit le petit prince qui ne comprit pas.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="11-10" id="319">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Clap your hands, one against the other,” the conceited man now directed him.<br/>The little prince clapped his hands.<br/>The conceited man raised his hat in a modest salute.<br/>"This is more entertaining than the visit to the king,” the little prince said to himself.<br/>And he began again to clap his hands, one against the other.<br/>The conceited man against raised his hat in salute.<br/>After five minutes of<br/>this exercise the little prince grew tired of the game’s monotony.<br/>"And what should one do to make the hat come down?”<br/>he asked. But the conceited man did not hear him.<br/>Conceited people never hear anything but praise.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Frappe tes mains l’une contre l’autre, conseilla donc le vaniteux.<br/>Le petit prince frappa ses mains l’une contre l’autre.<br/>Le vaniteux salua modestement en soulevant son chapeau.<br/>' Ça c’est plus amusant que la visite au roi ', se dit en lui- même le petit prince.<br/>Et il recommença de frapper ses mains l’une contre l’autre.<br/>Le vaniteux recommença de saluer en soulevant son chapeau.<br/>Après cinq minutes d’exercice le petit prince se fatigua de la monotonie du jeu :<br/>– Et, pour que le chapeau tombe, demanda-t-il, que faut-il faire ?<br/>Mais le vaniteux ne l’entendit pas.<br/>Les vaniteux n’entendent jamais que les louanges.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="320">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Do you really admire me very much?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Est-ce que tu m’admires vraiment beaucoup ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="321">
  <src xml:lang="EN">he demanded of the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">demanda- t-il au petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="322">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What does that mean, ‘admire’?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Qu’est-ce que signifie admirer ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="323">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"To admire means that you regard me as the handsomest, the best-dressed, the richest, and the most intelligent man on this planet.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Admirer signifie reconnaître que je suis l’homme le plus beau, le mieux habillé, le plus riche et le plus intelligent de la planète.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="324">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But you are the only man on your planet!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais tu es seul sur ta planète !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="325">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Do me this kindness.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Fais-moi ce plaisir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="326">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Admire me just the same.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Admire-moi quand même !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="327">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I admire you,” said the little prince, shrugging his shoulders slightly, "but what is there in that to interest you so much?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je t’admire, dit le petit prince, en haussant un peu les épaules, mais en quoi cela peut-il bien t’intéresser ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="328">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And the little prince went away.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et le petit prince s’en fut.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="329">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"The grown-ups are certainly very odd,” he said to himself, as he continued on his journey.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' Les grandes personnes sont décidément bien bizarres ', se dit-il simplement en lui-même durant son voyage.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="330">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The next planet was inhabited by a tippler.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La planète suivante était habitée par un buveur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="331">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This was a very short visit, but it plunged the little prince into deep dejection.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cette visite fut très courte, mais elle plongea le petit prince dans une grande mélancolie :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="332">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What are you doing there?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Que fais-tu là ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="333">
  <src xml:lang="EN">he said to the tippler, whom he found settled down in silence before a collection of empty bottles and also a collection of full bottles.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">dit-il au buveur, qu’il trouva installé en silence devant une collection de bouteilles vides et une collection de bouteilles pleines.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="334">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I am drinking,” replied the tippler, with a lugubrious air.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je bois, répondit le buveur, d’un air lugubre.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="335">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Why are you drinking?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Pourquoi bois-tu ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="336">
  <src xml:lang="EN">demanded the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">lui demanda le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="337">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"So that I may forget,” replied the tippler.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Pour oublier, répondit le buveur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-3" id="338">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Forget what?”<br/>inquired the little prince, who already<br/>was sorry for him.<br/>"Forget that I am ashamed,” the tippler confessed, hanging his head.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Pour oublier quoi ?<br/>s’enquit le petit prince qui déjà le plaignait.<br/>– Pour oublier que j’ai honte, avoua le buveur en baissant la tête.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="339">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ashamed of what?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Honte de quoi ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="6-5" id="340">
  <src xml:lang="EN">insisted the little prince, who wanted to help him.<br/>"Ashamed of drinking!”<br/>The tippler brought his speech to an end, and shut himself up in an<br/>impregnable silence.<br/>And the little prince went away, puzzled.<br/>"The grown-ups are certainly very, very odd,” he said to himself, as he continued on his journey.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">s’informa le petit prince qui désirait le secourir.<br/>– Honte de boire !<br/>acheva le buveur qui s’enferma définitivement dans le silence.<br/>Et le petit prince s’en fut, perplexe.<br/>' Les grandes personnes sont décidément très très bizarres ', se disait-il en lui-même durant le voyage.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="341">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The fourth planet belonged to a businessman.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La quatrième planète était celle du businessman.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="342">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This man was so much occupied that he did not even raise his head at the little prince’s arrival.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cet homme était si occupé qu’il ne leva même pas la tête à l’arrivée du petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="343">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” the little prince said to him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, lui dit celui-ci.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="344">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Your cigarette has gone out.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Votre cigarette est éteinte.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="345">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Three and two make five.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Trois et deux font cinq.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="346">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Five and seven make twelve.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cinq et sept douze.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="347">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Twelve and three make fifteen.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Douze et trois quinze.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="348">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Good morning. Fifteen and seven make twenty-two.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Bonjour. Quinze et sept vingt-deux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="349">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Twenty-two and six make twenty-eight.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vingt-deux et six vingt-huit.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="350">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I haven’t time to light it again.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Pas le temps de la rallumer.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="351">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Twenty-six and five make thirty-one.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vingt-six et cinq trente et un.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="352">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Phew ! Then that makes five-hundredand- one-million, six-hundred-twenty-two-thousand, seven-hundred-thirty-one.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ouf ! Ça fait donc cinq cent un millions six cent vingt- deux mille sept cent trente et un.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="353">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Five hundred million what?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Cinq cents millions de quoi ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="7-4" id="354">
  <src xml:lang="EN">asked the little prince.<br/>"Eh? Are you still there?<br/>Five-hundred-andone million, I can’t stop...<br/>I have so much to do!<br/>I am concerned with matters of consequence.<br/>I don’t amuse myself with balderdash.<br/>Two and five make seven...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Hein ? Tu es toujours là ?<br/>Cinq cent un millions de… je ne sais plus… J’ai tellement de travail !<br/>Je suis sérieux, moi, je ne m’amuse pas à des balivernes !<br/>Deux et cinq sept…<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="355">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Five-hundred-and-one million what?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Cinq cent un millions de quoi ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="356">
  <src xml:lang="EN">repeated the little prince, who never in his life had let go of a question once he had asked it.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">répéta le petit prince qui jamais de sa vie, n’avait renoncé à une question, une fois qu’il l’avait posée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="357">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The businessman raised his head.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le businessman leva la tête :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="358">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"During the fifty-four years that I have inhabited this planet, I have been disturbed only three times.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Depuis cinquante-quatre ans que j’habite cette planète- ci, je n’ai été dérangé que trois fois.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="359">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The first time was twenty-two years ago, when some giddy goose fell from goodness knows where.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La première fois ç’a été, il y a vingt-deux ans, par un hanneton qui était tombé Dieu sait d’où.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="360">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He made the most frightful noise that resounded all over the place, and I made four mistakes in my addition.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il répandait un bruit épouvantable, et j’ai fait quatre erreurs dans une addition.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="361">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The second time, eleven years ago, I was disturbed by an attack of rheumatism.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La seconde fois ç’a été, il y a onze ans, par une crise de rhumatisme.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="362">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I don’t get enough exercise.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je manque d’exercice.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="363">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have no time for loafing.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je n’ai pas le temps de flâner.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="364">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The third time, well, this is it!<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je suis sérieux, moi.<br/>La troisième fois… la voici !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="365">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I was saying, then, five -hundred-and-one millions”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je disais donc cinq cent un millions…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="366">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Millions of what?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Millions de quoi ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="367">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The businessman suddenly realised that there was no hope of being left in peace until he answered this question.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le businessman comprit qu’il n’était point d’espoir de paix :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="368">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Millions of those little objects,” he said, "which one sometimes sees in the sky.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Millions de ces petites choses que l’on voit quelquefois dans le ciel.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="29-37" id="369">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Flies?” "Oh, no. Little glittering objects.”<br/>"Bees?” "Oh, no. Little golden objects that set lazy men to idle dreaming.<br/>As for me, I am concerned with matters of consequence.<br/>There is no time for idle dreaming in my life.”<br/>"Ah! You mean the stars?”<br/>"Yes, that’s it.<br/>The stars.” "And what do you do with five-hundred millions of stars?”<br/>"Five-hundred-and-one million, six-hundred-twenty-two thousand, seven-hundred-thirty-one.<br/>I am concerned with matters of consequence: I am accurate.”<br/>"And what do you do with these stars?”<br/>"What do I do with them?”<br/>"Yes.” "Nothing. I own them.” "You own the stars?”<br/>"Yes.” "But I have already seen a king who...”<br/>"Kings do not own, they reign over.<br/>It is a very different matter.”<br/>"And what good does it do you to own the stars?”<br/>"It does me the good of making me rich.”<br/>"And what good does it do you to be rich?”<br/>"It makes it possible for me to buy more stars, if any are ever discovered.”<br/>"This man,” the little prince said to himself, "reasons a little like my poor tippler...”<br/>Nevertheless, he still had some more questions.<br/>"How is it possible for one to own the stars?”<br/>"To whom do they belong?”<br/>the businessman retorted, peevishly.<br/>"I don’t know.<br/>To nobody.” "Then they belong to me, because I was the first person to think of it.”<br/>"Is that all that is necessary?”<br/>"Certainly. When you find a diamond that belongs to nobody, it is yours.<br/>When you discover an island that belongs to nobody, it is yours.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Des mouches ?<br/>– Mais non, des petites choses qui brillent.<br/>– Des abeilles ?<br/>– Mais non. Des petites choses dorées qui font rêvasser les fainéants.<br/>Mais je suis sérieux, moi !<br/>Je n’ai pas le temps de rêvasser.<br/>– Ah ! des étoiles ?<br/>– C’est bien ça.<br/>Des étoiles.<br/>– Et que fais-tu de cinq cents millions d’étoiles ?<br/>– Cinq cent un millions six cent vingt-deux mille sept cent trente et un.<br/>Je suis sérieux, moi, je suis précis.<br/>– Et que fais-tu de ces étoiles ?<br/>– Ce que j’en fais ?<br/>– Oui.<br/>– Rien. Je les possède.<br/>– Tu possèdes les étoiles ?<br/>– Oui.<br/>– Mais j’ai déjà vu un roi qui…<br/>– Les rois ne possèdent pas.<br/>Ils ' règnent ' sur.<br/>C’est très différent.<br/>– Et à quoi cela te sert-il de posséder les étoiles ?<br/>– Ça me sert à être riche.<br/>– Et à quoi cela te sert-il d’être riche ?<br/>– À acheter d’autres étoiles, si quelqu’un en trouve.<br/>' Celui-là, se dit en lui-même le petit prince, il raisonne un peu comme mon ivrogne.<br/>' Cependant il posa encore des questions :<br/>– Comment peut-on posséder les étoiles ?<br/>– À qui sont-elles ?<br/>riposta, grincheux, le businessman.<br/>– Je ne sais pas.<br/>À personne.<br/>– Alors elles sont à moi, car j’y ai pensé le premier.<br/>– Ça suffit ?<br/>– Bien sûr. Quand tu trouves un diamant qui n’est à personne, il est à toi.<br/>Quand tu trouves une île qui n’est à personne, elle est à toi.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="370">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When you get an idea before any one else, you take out a patent on it: it is yours.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quand tu as une idée le premier, tu la fais breveter : elle est à toi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="371">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So with me: I own the stars, because nobody else before me ever thought of owning them.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et moi je possède les étoiles, puisque jamais personne avant moi n’a songé à les posséder.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="372">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, that is true,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça c’est vrai, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="373">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"And what do you do with them?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et qu’en fais-tu ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="374">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I administer them,” replied the businessman.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je les gère.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="375">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I count them and recount them.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je les compte et je les recompte, dit le businessman.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="376">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is difficult.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est difficile.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="377">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But I am a man who is naturally interested in matters of consequence.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais je suis un homme sérieux !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="378">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince was still not satisfied.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince n’était pas satisfait encore.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="379">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"If I owned a silk scarf,” he said, "I could put it around my neck and take it away with me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Moi, si je possède un foulard, je puis le mettre autour de mon cou et l’emporter.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="380">
  <src xml:lang="EN">If I owned a flower, I could pluck that flower and take it away with me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Moi, si je possède une fleur, je puis cueillir ma fleur et l’emporter.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="381">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But you cannot pluck the stars from heaven...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais tu ne peux pas cueillir les étoiles !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="382">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"No. But I can put them in the bank.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Non, mais je puis les placer en banque.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="383">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Whatever does that mean?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Qu’est-ce que ça veut dire ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="384">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That means that I write the number of my stars on a little paper.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça veut dire que j’écris sur un petit papier le nombre de mes étoiles.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="385">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And then I put this paper in a drawer and lock it with a key.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et puis j’enferme à clef ce papier-là dans un tiroir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="19-21" id="386">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"And that is all?”<br/>"That is enough,” said the businessman.<br/>"It is entertaining,” thought the little prince.<br/>"It is rather poetic.<br/>But it is of no great consequence.”<br/>On matters of consequence, the little prince had ideas, which were very different from those of the grown-ups.<br/>"I myself own a flower,” he continued his conversation with the businessman, "which I water every day.<br/>I own three volcanoes, which I clean out every week (for I also clean out the one that is extinct; one never knows).<br/>It is of some use to my volcanoes, and it is of some use to my flower, that I own them.<br/>But you are of no use to the stars...”<br/>The businessman opened his mouth, but he found nothing to say in answer.<br/>And the little prince went away.<br/>"The grown-ups are certainly altogether extraordinary,” he said simply, talking to himself as he continued on his journey.<br/>The fifth planet was very strange.<br/>It was the smallest of all.<br/>There was just enough room on it for a street lamp and a lamplighter.<br/>The little prince was not able to reach any explanation of the use of a street lamp and a lamplighter, somewhere in the heavens, on a planet, which had no people, and not one house.<br/>But he said to himself, nevertheless: "It may well be that this man is absurd.<br/>But he is not so absurd as the king, the conceited man, the businessman, and the tippler.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Et c’est tout ?<br/>– Ça suffit !<br/>' C’est amusant, pensa le petit prince.<br/>C’est assez poétique.<br/>Mais ce n’est pas très sérieux.<br/>'<br/>Le petit prince avait sur les choses sérieuses des idées très différentes des idées des grandes personnes.<br/>– Moi, dit-il encore, je possède une fleur que j’arrose tous les jours.<br/>Je possède trois volcans que je ramone toutes les semaines.<br/>Car je ramone aussi celui qui est éteint.<br/>On ne sait jamais.<br/>C’est utile à mes volcans, et c’est utile à ma fleur, que je les possède.<br/>Mais tu n’es pas utile aux étoiles… Le businessman ouvrit la bouche mais ne trouva rien à répondre, et le petit prince s’en fut.<br/>' Les grandes personnes sont décidément tout à fait extraordinaires ', se disait-il simplement en lui-même durant le voyage.<br/>La cinquième planète était très curieuse.<br/>C’était la plus petite de toutes.<br/>Il y avait là juste assez de place pour loger un réverbère et un allumeur de réverbères.<br/>Le petit prince ne parvenait pas à s’expliquer à quoi pouvaient servir, quelque part dans le ciel, sur une planète sans maison, ni population, un réverbère et un allumeur de réverbères.<br/>Cependant il se dit en lui-même :<br/>' Peut-être bien que cet homme est absurde.<br/>Cependant il est moins absurde que le roi, que le vaniteux, que le businessman et que le buveur.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="387">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For at least his work has</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Au moins son travail a-t-il un sens.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-2" id="388">
  <src xml:lang="EN">some meaning.<br/>When he lights his street lamp, it is as if he brought one more star to life, or one flower.<br/>When he puts out his lamp, he sends the flower, or the star, to sleep.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quand il allume son réverbère, c’est comme s’il faisait naître une étoile de plus, ou une fleur.<br/>Quand il éteint son réverbère, ça endort la fleur ou l’étoile.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="389">
  <src xml:lang="EN">That is a beautiful occupation.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est une occupation très jolie.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="390">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And since it is beautiful, it is truly useful.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est véritablement utile puisque c’est joli.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="391">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When he arrived on the planet he respectfully saluted the lamplighter.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">'</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="392">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Lorsqu’il aborda la planète il salua respectueusement l’allumeur :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="393">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Why have you just put out your lamp?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour. Pourquoi viens-tu d’éteindre ton réverbère ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="394">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Those are the orders,” replied the lamplighter.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est la consigne, répondit l’allumeur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="16-12" id="395">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning.”<br/>"What are the orders?”<br/>"The orders are that I put out my lamp.<br/>Good evening.”<br/>And he lighted his lamp again.<br/>"But why<br/>have you just lighted it again?”<br/>"Those are the orders,” replied the lamplighter.<br/>"I do not understand,” said the little prince.<br/>"There is nothing to understand,” said the lamplighter.<br/>"Orders are orders.<br/>Good morning.”<br/>And<br/>he put out his lamp.<br/>Then he mopped his forehead with a handkerchief decorated with red squares.<br/>"I follow a terrible profession.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Bonjour.<br/>– Qu’est-ce que la consigne ?<br/>– C’est d’éteindre mon réverbère.<br/>Bonsoir. Et il le ralluma.<br/>– Mais pourquoi viens-tu de le rallumer ?<br/>– C’est la consigne, répondit l’allumeur.<br/>– Je ne comprends pas, dit le petit prince.<br/>– Il n’y a rien à comprendre, dit l’allumeur.<br/>La consigne c’est la consigne.<br/>Bonjour. Et il éteignit son réverbère.<br/>Puis il s’épongea le front avec un mouchoir à carreaux rouges.<br/>– Je fais là un métier terrible.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="396">
  <src xml:lang="EN">In the old days it was reasonable.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’était raisonnable autrefois.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="397">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I put the lamp out in the morning,</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’éteignais le matin et j’allumais le soir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="398">
  <src xml:lang="EN">and in the evening I lighted it again.<br/>I had the rest of the day for relaxation and the rest of the night for sleep.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’avais le reste du jour pour me reposer, et le reste de la nuit pour dormir…<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="399">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"And the orders have been changed since that time?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Et, depuis cette époque, la consigne a changé ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="400">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"The orders have not been changed,” said the lamplighter.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– La consigne n’a pas changé, dit l’allumeur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="401">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is the tragedy!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est bien là le drame !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="402">
  <src xml:lang="EN">From year to year the planet has turned more rapidly and the orders have not been changed!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La planète d’année en année a tourné de plus en plus vite, et la consigne n’a pas changé !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="403">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Then what?” asked the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Alors ? dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="404">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Then the planet now makes a complete turn every minute, and I no longer have a single second for repose.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Alors maintenant qu’elle fait un tour par minute, je n’ai plus une seconde de repos.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="405">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Once every minute I have to light my lamp and put it out!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’allume et j’éteins une fois par minute !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-3" id="406">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is very funny!<br/>A day lasts only one minute, here where you live!”<br/>"It is not funny at all!”<br/>said the lamplighter.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça c’est drôle !<br/>Les jours chez toi durent une minute !<br/>– Ce n’est pas drôle du tout, dit l’allumeur.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="407">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"While we have been talking together a month has</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça fait déjà un mois que nous parlons ensemble.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="408">
  <src xml:lang="EN">gone by.” "A month?” "Yes, a month.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Un mois ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="409">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Thirty minutes.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Oui. Trente minutes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="410">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Thirty days. Good evening.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Trente jours !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-2" id="411">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he lighted his lamp again.<br/>As the<br/>little prince watched him, he felt that he loved this lamplighter who was so faithful to his orders.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Bonsoir. Et il ralluma son réverbère.<br/>Le petit prince le regarda et il aima cet allumeur qui était tellement fidèle à la consigne.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="412">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He remembered the sunsets, which he himself had gone to seek, in other days, merely by pulling up his chair; and he wanted to help his friend.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il se souvint des couchers de soleil que lui-même allait autrefois chercher, en tirant sa chaise.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-3" id="413">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"You know,” he said, "I can tell you a way you can rest whenever you want to...”<br/>"I always want to rest,” said the lamplighter.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il voulut aider son ami :<br/>– Tu sais… je connais un moyen de te reposer quand tu voudras…<br/>– Je veux toujours, dit l’allumeur.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="414">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For it is possible for a man to be faithful and lazy at the same time.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Car on peut être, à la fois, fidèle et paresseux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="415">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince went on with his explanation: "Your planet is so small that three strides will take you all the way around it.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince poursuivit :<br/>– Ta planète est tellement petite que tu en fais le tour en trois enjambées.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="416">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To be always in the sunshine, you need only walk along rather slowly.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu n’as qu’à marcher assez lentement pour rester toujours au soleil.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="417">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When you want to rest, you will walk and the day will last as long as you like.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Quand tu voudras te reposer tu marcheras… et le jour durera aussi longtemps que tu voudras.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="418">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That doesn’t do me much good,” said the lamplighter.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça ne m’avance pas à grand’chose, dit l’allumeur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="419">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"The one thing I love in life is to sleep.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce que j’aime dans la vie, c’est dormir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="420">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Then you’re unlucky,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce n’est pas de chance, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="421">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I am unlucky,” said the lamplighter.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce n’est pas de chance, dit l’allumeur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-2" id="422">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning.”<br/>And he put out his lamp.<br/>"That man,” said the little prince to himself, as he continued farther on his journey, "that man would be scorned by all the others: by the king, by the conceited man, by the tippler, by the businessman.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Bonjour. Et il éteignit son réverbère.<br/>' Celui-là, se dit le petit prince, tandis qu’il poursuivait plus loin son voyage, celui-là serait méprisé par tous les autres, par le roi, par le vaniteux, par le buveur, par le businessman.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="423">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Nevertheless he is the only one of them all who does not seem to me ridiculous.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cependant c’est le seul qui ne me paraisse pas ridicule.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-4" id="424">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Perhaps that is because he is thinking of something else besides himself.”<br/>He breathed a sigh of regret, and said to himself, again: "That man is the only one of them all whom I could have made my friend.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est, peut-être, parce qu’il s’occupe d’autre chose que de soi-même.<br/>'<br/>Il eut un soupir de regret et se dit encore :<br/>' Celui-là est le seul dont j’eusse pu faire mon ami.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="425">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But his planet is indeed too small.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais sa planète est vraiment trop petite.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="426">
  <src xml:lang="EN">There is no room on it for two people...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il n’y a pas de place pour deux… '</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="427">
  <src xml:lang="EN">What the little prince did not dare confess was that he was sorry most of all to leave this planet, because it was blest every day with 1440 sunsets!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce que le petit prince n’osait pas s’avouer, c’est qu’il regrettait cette planète bénie à cause, surtout, des mille quatre cent quarante couchers de soleil par vingt-quatre heures !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="428">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The sixth planet was ten times larger than the last one.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La sixième planète était une planète dix fois plus vaste.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="429">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was inhabited by an old gentleman who wrote voluminous books.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elle était habitée par un vieux Monsieur qui écrivait d’énormes livres.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="430">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Oh, look! Here is an explorer!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Tiens ! voilà un explorateur !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="431">
  <src xml:lang="EN">he exclaimed to himself when he saw the little prince coming.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">s’écria-t-il, quand il aperçut le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="432">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince sat down on the table and panted a little.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince s’assit sur la table et souffla un peu.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="433">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He had already travelled so much and so far!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il avait déjà tant voyagé !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="10-8" id="434">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Where do you come from?”<br/>the old gentleman said to him.<br/>"What is that big book?”<br/>said the little prince.<br/>"What are you doing?”<br/>"I am a geographer,” the old gentleman said to him.<br/>"What is a geographer?”<br/>asked the little prince.<br/>"A geographer is a scholar who knows the<br/>location of all the seas, rivers, towns, mountains, and deserts.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– D’où viens-tu ?<br/>lui dit le vieux Monsieur.<br/>– Quel est ce gros livre ?<br/>dit le petit prince.<br/>Que faites-vous ici ?<br/>– Je suis géographe, dit le vieux Monsieur.<br/>– Qu’est-ce qu’un géographe ?<br/>– C’est un savant qui connaît où se trouvent les mers, les fleuves, les villes, les montagnes et les déserts.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="435">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is very interesting,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça c’est bien intéressant, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="436">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Here at last is a man who has a real profession!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça c’est enfin un véritable métier !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="437">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he cast a look around him at the planet of the geographer.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et il jeta un coup d’oeil autour de lui sur la planète du géographe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="438">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was the most magnificent and stately planet that he had ever seen.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il n’avait jamais vu encore une planète aussi majestueuse.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="439">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Your planet is very beautiful,” he said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Elle est bien belle, votre planète.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="440">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Has it any oceans?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Est-ce qu’il y a des océans ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="441">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I couldn’t tell you,” said the geographer.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je ne puis pas le savoir, dit le géographe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="442">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah!” The little prince was disappointed.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! (Le petit prince était déçu.)</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="443">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Has it any mountains?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et des montagnes ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="18-17" id="444">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I couldn’t tell you,” said the geographer.<br/>"And towns, and rivers, and deserts?”<br/>"I couldn’t tell you that, either.”<br/>"But you are a geographer!”<br/>"Exactly,” the geographer said.<br/>"But I am not an explorer.<br/>I haven’t a single explorer on my<br/>planet. It is not the geographer who goes out to count the towns, the rivers, the mountains, the seas, the oceans, and the deserts.<br/>The geographer is much too important to go loafing about.<br/>He does not leave his desk.<br/>But he receives the explorers in his study.<br/>He asks them questions, and he notes down what they recall of their travels.<br/>And if the recollections of any one among them seem interesting to him, the geographer orders an inquiry into that explorer’s moral character.”<br/>"Why is that?”<br/>"Because an explorer who told lies would bring disaster on the books of the geographer.<br/>So would an explorer who drank too much.”<br/>"Why is that?”<br/>asked the little prince.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je ne puis pas le savoir, dit le géographe.<br/>– Et des villes et des fleuves et des déserts ?<br/>– Je ne puis pas le savoir non plus, dit le géographe.<br/>– Mais vous êtes géographe !<br/>– C’est exact, dit le géographe, mais je ne suis pas explorateur.<br/>Je manque absolument d’explorateurs.<br/>Ce n’est pas le géographe qui va faire le compte des villes, des fleuves, des montagnes, des mers, des océans et des déserts.<br/>Le géographe est trop important pour flâner.<br/>Il ne quitte pas son bureau.<br/>Mais il y reçoit les explorateurs.<br/>Il les interroge, et il prend en note leurs souvenirs.<br/>Et si les souvenirs de l’un d’entre eux lui paraissent intéressants, le géographe fait faire une enquête sur la moralité de l’explorateur.<br/>– Pourquoi ça ?<br/>– Parce qu’un explorateur qui mentirait entraînerait des catastrophes dans les livres de géographie.<br/>Et aussi un explorateur qui boirait trop.<br/>– Pourquoi ça ?<br/>fit le petit prince.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="445">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Because intoxicated men see double.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Parce que les ivrognes voient double.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="446">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then the geographer would note down two mountains in a</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors le géographe noterait deux montagnes, là où il n’y en a qu’une seule.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="447">
  <src xml:lang="EN">place where there was only one.”<br/>"I know some one,” said the little prince, "who would make a bad explorer.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je connais quelqu’un, dit le petit prince, qui serait mauvais explorateur.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="448">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"That is possible.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est possible.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="449">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then, when the moral character of the explorer is shown to be good, an inquiry</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Donc, quand la moralité de l’explorateur paraît bonne, on fait une enquête sur sa découverte.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="450">
  <src xml:lang="EN">is ordered into his discovery.”<br/>"One goes to see it?”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– On va voir ?<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="451">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"No. That would be too complicated.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Non. C’est trop compliqué.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="452">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But one requires the explorer to furnish proofs.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais on exige de l’explorateur qu’il fournisse des preuves.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="6-5" id="453">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For example,<br/>if the discovery in question is that of a large mountain, one requires that large stones be brought back from it.”<br/>The geographer was suddenly stirred to excitement.<br/>"But you come from far away!<br/>You are an explorer!<br/>You shall describe your planet to me!”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">S’il s’agit par exemple de la découverte d’une grosse montagne, on exige qu’il en rapporte de grosses pierres.<br/>Le géographe soudain s’émut.<br/>– Mais toi, tu viens de loin !<br/>Tu es explorateur !<br/>Tu vas me décrire ta planète !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="454">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And, having opened his big register, the geographer sharpened his pencil.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et le géographe, ayant ouvert son registre, tailla son crayon.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="455">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The recitals of explorers are put down first in pencil.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On note d’abord au crayon les récits des explorateurs.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="456">
  <src xml:lang="EN">One waits until the explorer has furnished proofs, before putting them down in ink.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On attend, pour noter à l’encre, que l’explorateur ait fourni des preuves.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-3" id="457">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Well?” said the geographer expectantly.<br/>"Oh, where I live,” said the little prince, "it is not very interesting.<br/>It is all so small.<br/>I have three volcanoes.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Alors ? interrogea le géographe.<br/>– Oh ! chez moi, dit le petit prince, ce n’est pas très intéressant, c’est tout petit.<br/>J’ai trois volcans.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="458">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Two volcanoes are active and the other is extinct.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Deux volcans en activité, et un volcan éteint.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="459">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But one never knows.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais on ne sait jamais.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="460">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"One never knows,” said the geographer.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– On ne sait jamais, dit le géographe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="461">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I have also a flower.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– J’ai aussi une fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="462">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"We do not record flowers,” said the geographer.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Nous ne notons pas les fleurs, dit le géographe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="463">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Why is that? The flower is the most beautiful thing on my planet!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Pourquoi ça !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="464">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"We do not record them,” said the geographer, "because they are ephemeral.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">c’est le plus joli !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="465">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What does that mean ‘ephemeral’?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Parce que les fleurs sont éphémères.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="466">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Geographies,” said the geographer, "are the books which, of all books, are most concerned with</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Qu’est-ce que signifie : ' éphémère ' ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="467">
  <src xml:lang="EN">matters of consequence.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Les géographies, dit le géographe, sont les livres les plus précieux de tous les livres.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="468">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They never become old-fashioned.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles ne se démodent jamais.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="469">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is very rarely that a mountain changes its position.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il est très rare qu’une montagne change de place.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="470">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is very rarely that an ocean empties itself of its waters.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il est très rare qu’un océan se vide de son eau.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="471">
  <src xml:lang="EN">We write of eternal things.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Nous écrivons des choses éternelles.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="472">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But extinct volcanoes may come to life again,” the little prince interrupted.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais les volcans éteints peuvent se réveiller, interrompit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="473">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What does that mean ‘ephemeral’?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Qu’est-ce que signifie ' éphémère ' ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="474">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Whether volcanoes are extinct or alive, it comes to the same thing for us,” said the geographer.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Que les volcans soient éteints ou soient éveillés, ça revient au même pour nous autres, dit le géographe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="475">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"The thing that matters to us is the mountain.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce qui compte pour nous, c’est la montagne.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="476">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It does not change.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elle ne change pas.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="8-6" id="477">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But what does that mean ‘ephemeral’?”<br/>repeated the little prince, who never in his life had let go of a question, once he had asked it.<br/>"It means, ‘which is in danger of speedy disappearance.’<br/>" "Is my flower in danger of speedy disappearance?”<br/>"Certainly it is.”<br/>"My flower is ephemeral,” the little prince said to himself, "and she has only four thorns to<br/>defend herself against the world.<br/>And I have left her on my planet, all alone!”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais qu’est-ce que signifie ' éphémère ' ?<br/>répéta le petit prince qui, de sa vie, n’avait renoncé à une question, une fois qu’il l’avait posée.<br/>– Ça signifie ' qui est menacé de disparition prochaine '.<br/>– Ma fleur est menacée de disparition prochaine ?<br/>– Bien sûr. Ma fleur est éphémère, se dit le petit prince, et elle n’a que quatre épines pour se défendre contre le monde !<br/>Et je l’ai laissée toute seule chez moi !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="478">
  <src xml:lang="EN">That was his first moment of regret.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce fut là son premier mouvement de regret.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="479">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he took courage once more.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais il reprit courage :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="480">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What place would you advise me to visit now?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Que me conseillez-vous d’aller visiter ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="481">
  <src xml:lang="EN">he asked. "The planet Earth,” replied the geographer.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">demanda-t-il.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="482">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It has a good reputation.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– La planète Terre, lui répondit le géographe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="483">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And the little prince went away, thinking of his flower.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elle a une bonne réputation… Et le petit prince s’en fut, songeant à sa fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="484">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So then the seventh planet was the Earth.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La septième planète fut donc la Terre.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="485">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The Earth is not just an ordinary planet!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La Terre n’est pas une planète quelconque !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="486">
  <src xml:lang="EN">One can count, there 111 kings (not forgetting, to be sure, the Negro kings among them), 7000 geographers, 900,000 businessmen, 7,500,000 tipplers, 311,000,000 conceited men, that is to say, about 2,000,000,000 grown-ups.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On y compte cent onze rois (en n’oubliant pas, bien sûr, les rois nègres), sept mille géographes, neuf cent mille businessmen, sept millions et demi d’ivrognes, trois cent onze millions de vaniteux, c’est-àdire environ deux milliards de grandes personnes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="487">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To give you an idea of the size of the Earth, I will tell you that before the invention of electricity it was necessary to maintain, over the whole of the six continents, a veritable army of 462,511 lamplighters for the street lamps.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Pour vous donner une idée des dimensions de la Terre je vous dirai qu’avant l’invention de l’électricité on y devait entretenir, sur l’ensemble des six continents, une véritable armée de quatre cent soixante-deux mille cinq cent onze allumeurs de réverbères.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="488">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Seen from a slight distance, that would make a splendid spectacle.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vu d’un peu loin ça faisait un effet splendide.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="489">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The movements of this army would be regulated like those of the ballet in the opera.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les mouvements de cette armée étaient réglés comme ceux d’un ballet d’opéra.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="490">
  <src xml:lang="EN">First would come the turn of the lamplighters of New Zealand and Australia.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">D’abord venait le tour des allumeurs de réverbères de Nouvelle-Zélande et d’Australie.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="9-13" id="491">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Having set their lamps alight, these would go off to sleep.<br/>Next, the lamplighters of China and Siberia would enter for their steps in the dance, and then they too would be waved back into the wings.<br/>After that would come the turn of the lamplighters of Russia and the Indies; then those of Africa and Europe, then those of South America; then those of North America.<br/>And never would they make a mistake in the order of their entry upon the stage.<br/>It would be magnificent.<br/>Only the man who was in charge of the single lamp at the North Pole, and his colleague who was responsible for the single lamp at the South Pole, only these two would live free from toil and care: they would be busy twice a year.<br/>When one wishes to play the wit, he sometimes wanders a little from the truth.<br/>I have not been altogether honest in what I have told you about the lamplighters.<br/>And I realise that I run the risk of giving a false idea of our planet to those who do not know it.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Puis ceux-ci, ayant allumé leurs lampions, s’en allaient dormir.<br/>Alors entraient à leur tour dans la danse les allumeurs de réverbères de Chine et de Sibérie.<br/>Puis eux aussi s’escamotaient dans les coulisses.<br/>Alors venait le tour des allumeurs de réverbères de Russie et des Indes.<br/>Puis de ceux d’Afrique et d’Europe.<br/>Puis de ceux d’Amérique du Sud.<br/>Puis de ceux d’Amérique du Nord.<br/>Et jamais ils ne se trompaient dans leur ordre d’entrée en scène.<br/>C’était grandiose.<br/>Seuls, l’allumeur de l’unique réverbère du pôle Nord, et son confrère de l’unique réverbère du pôle Sud, menaient des vies d’oisiveté et de nonchalance : ils travaillaient deux fois par an.<br/>Quand on veut faire de l’esprit, il arrive que l’on mente un peu.<br/>Je n’ai pas été très honnête en vous parlant des allumeurs de réverbères.<br/>Je risque de donner une fausse idée de notre planète à ceux qui ne la connaissent pas.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="492">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Men occupy a very small place upon the Earth.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les hommes occupent très peu de place sur la terre.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="493">
  <src xml:lang="EN">If the two billion inhabitants who people its surface were all to stand upright and somewhat crowded together, as they do for some big public assembly, they could easily be put into one public square twenty miles long and twenty miles wide.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Si les deux milliards d’habitants qui peuplent la terre se tenaient debout et un peu serrés, comme pour un meeting, ils logeraient aisément sur une place publique de vingt milles de long sur vingt milles de large.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="494">
  <src xml:lang="EN">All humanity could be piled up on a small Pacific islet.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On pourrait entasser l’humanité sur le moindre petit îlot du Pacifique.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="495">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The grown-ups, to be sure, will not believe you when you tell them that.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les grandes personnes, bien sûr, ne vous croiront pas.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="496">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They imagine that they fill a great deal of space.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles s’imaginent tenir beaucoup de place.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="497">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They fancy themselves as important as the baobabs.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles se voient importantes comme des baobabs.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="498">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You should advise them, then, to make their own calculations.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vous leur conseillerez donc de faire le calcul.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="499">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They adore figures, and that will please them.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles adorent les chiffres : ça leur plaira.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="500">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But do not waste your time on this extra task.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais ne perdez pas votre temps à ce pensum.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="501">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is unnecessary.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est inutile.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="502">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You have, I know, confidence in me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Vous avez confiance en moi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="503">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When the little prince arrived on the Earth, he was very much surprised not to see any people.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince, une fois sur terre, fut donc bien surpris de ne voir personne.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="504">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He was beginning to be afraid he had come to the wrong planet, when a coil of gold, the colour of the moonlight, flashed across the sand.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il avait déjà peur de s’être trompé de planète, quand un anneau couleur de lune remua dans le sable.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="505">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good evening,” said the little prince courteously.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonne nuit, fit le petit prince à tout hasard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="506">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good evening,” said the snake.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonne nuit, fit le serpent.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="507">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What planet is this on which I have come down?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Sur quelle planète suis-je tombé ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="508">
  <src xml:lang="EN">asked the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">demanda le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="509">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"This is the Earth; this is Africa,” the snake answered.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Sur la Terre, en Afrique, répondit le serpent.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="510">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah! Then there are no people on the Earth?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! … Il n’y a donc personne sur la Terre ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="511">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"This is the desert.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ici c’est le désert.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="512">
  <src xml:lang="EN">There are no people in the desert.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il n’y a personne dans les déserts.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="513">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The Earth is large,” said the snake.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">La Terre est grande, dit le serpent.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="514">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince sat down on a stone, and raised his eyes toward the sky.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince s’assit sur une pierre et leva les yeux vers le ciel :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="515">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I wonder,” he said, "whether the stars are set alight in heaven so that one day each one of us</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je me demande, dit-il, si les étoiles sont éclairées afin que chacun puisse un jour retrouver la sienne.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="37-27" id="516">
  <src xml:lang="EN">may find his own again...<br/>Look at my planet.<br/>It is right there above us.<br/>But how far away it is!”<br/>"It is beautiful,” the snake said.<br/>"What has brought you here?”<br/>"I have been having some trouble with a flower,” said the little prince.<br/>"Ah!” said the snake.<br/>And<br/>they were both silent.<br/>"Where are the men?”<br/>the little prince at last took up the conversation again.<br/>"It is a little lonely in the desert...”<br/>"It is also lonely among men,” the snake said.<br/>The little prince gazed at him for a long time.<br/>"You are a funny animal,” he said at last.<br/>"You are no thicker than a finger...”<br/>"But I am more powerful than the finger of a king,” said the snake.<br/>The little prince smiled.<br/>"You are not very powerful.<br/>You haven’t even any feet.<br/>You cannot even<br/>travel...”<br/>"I can carry you farther than any ship could take you,” said the snake.<br/>He twined himself around the little prince’s ankle, like a golden bracelet.<br/>"Whomever I touch, I send back to the earth from whence he came,” the snake spoke again.<br/>"But<br/>you are innocent and true, and you come from a star...”<br/>The little prince made no reply.<br/>"You move me to pity, you are so weak on this Earth made of<br/>granite,” the snake said.<br/>"I can help you, some day, if you grow too homesick for your own planet.<br/>I can...” "Oh! I understand you very well,” said the little prince.<br/>"But why do you always speak in<br/>riddles?” "I solve them all,” said the snake.<br/>And they were both silent.<br/>The little prince crossed the desert and met with only one flower.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Regarde ma planète.<br/>Elle est juste au-dessus de nous… Mais comme elle est loin !<br/>– Elle est belle, dit le serpent.<br/>Que viens-tu faire ici ?<br/>– J’ai des difficultés avec une fleur, dit le petit prince.<br/>– Ah ! fit le serpent.<br/>Et ils se turent.<br/>– Où sont les hommes ?<br/>reprit enfin le petit prince.<br/>On est un peu seul dans le désert…<br/>– On est seul aussi chez les hommes, dit le serpent.<br/>Le petit prince le regarda longtemps :<br/>– Tu es une drôle de bête, lui dit-il enfin, mince comme un doigt…<br/>– Mais je suis plus puissant que le doigt d’un roi, dit le serpent.<br/>Le petit prince eut un sourire :<br/>– Tu n’es pas bien puissant… tu n’as même pas de pattes… tu ne peux même pas voyager…<br/>– Je puis t’emporter plus loin qu’un navire, dit le serpent.<br/>Il s’enroula autour de la cheville du petit prince, comme un bracelet d’or :<br/>– Celui que je touche, je le rends à la terre dont il est sorti, dit-il encore.<br/>Mais tu es pur et tu viens d’une étoile… Le petit prince ne répondit rien.<br/>– Tu me fais pitié, toi si faible, sur cette Terre de granit.<br/>Je puis t’aider un jour si tu regrettes trop ta planète.<br/>Je puis…<br/>– Oh ! J’ai très bien compris, fit le petit prince, mais pourquoi parles-tu toujours par énigmes ?<br/>– Je les résous toutes, dit le serpent.<br/>Et ils se turent.<br/>Le petit prince traversa le désert et ne rencontra qu’une fleur.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="517">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was a flower with three petals, a flower of no account at all.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Une fleur à trois pétales, une fleur de rien du tout…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="518">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="519">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” said the flower.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit la fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="8-9" id="520">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Where are the men?”<br/>the little prince asked, politely.<br/>The flower had once seen a caravan<br/>passing. "Men?” she echoed. "I think there are six or seven of them in existence.<br/>I saw them, several<br/>years ago. But one never knows where to find them.<br/>The wind blows them away.<br/>They have no roots, and that makes their life very difficult.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Où sont les hommes ?<br/>demanda poliment le petit prince.<br/>La fleur, un jour, avait vu passer une caravane :<br/>– Les hommes ?<br/>Il en existe, je crois, six ou sept.<br/>Je les ai aperçus il y a des années.<br/>Mais on ne sait jamais où les trouver.<br/>Le vent les promène.<br/>Ils manquent de racines, ça les gêne beaucoup.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="521">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Goodbye,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Adieu, fit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="522">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Goodbye,” said the flower.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Adieu, dit la fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="523">
  <src xml:lang="EN">After that, the little prince climbed a high mountain.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince fit l’ascension d’une haute montagne.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="524">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The only mountains he had ever known were the three volcanoes, which came up to his knees.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les seules montagnes qu’il eût jamais connues étaient les trois volcans qui lui arrivaient au genou.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="525">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he used the extinct volcano as a footstool.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et il se servait du volcan éteint comme d’un tabouret.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="526">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"From a mountain as high as this one,” he said to himself, "I shall be able to see the whole planet at one glance, and all the people...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' D’une montagne haute comme celle-ci, se dit-il donc, j’apercevrai d’un coup toute la planète et tous les hommes… ' Mais il n’aperçut rien que des aiguilles de roc bien aiguisées.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="19-13" id="527">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he saw nothing, save peaks of rock that were sharpened like needles.<br/>"Good morning,” he said courteously.<br/>"Good morning...<br/>Good morning...<br/>Good morning,” answered the echo.<br/>"Who are you?”<br/>said the little prince.<br/>"Who are you...<br/>Who are you... Who are you?” answered the echo.<br/>"Be my friends.<br/>I am all alone,” he said.<br/>"I am all alone...all alone...all alone,” answered the echo.<br/>"What a queer planet!”<br/>he thought. "It is altogether dry, and altogether pointed, and altogether<br/>harsh and forbidding.<br/>And the people have no imagination.<br/>They repeat whatever one says to<br/>them... On my planet I had a flower; she always was the first to speak...”<br/>But it happened that after walking for a long time through sand, and rocks, and snow, the little prince at last came upon a road.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit-il à tout hasard.<br/>– Bonjour… Bonjour… Bonjour… répondit l’écho.<br/>– Qui êtes-vous ?<br/>dit le petit prince.<br/>– Qui êtes-vous… qui êtes-vous… qui êtes-vous… répondit l’écho.<br/>– Soyez mes amis, je suis seul, dit-il.<br/>– Je suis seul… je suis seul… je suis seul… répondit l’écho.<br/>' Quelle drôle de planète !<br/>pensa-t-il alors.<br/>Elle est toute sèche, et toute pointue et toute salée.<br/>Et les hommes manquent d’imagination.<br/>Ils répètent ce qu’on leur dit… Chez moi j’avais une fleur : elle parlait toujours la première… '<br/>Mais il arriva que le petit prince, ayant longtemps marché à travers les sables, les rocs et les neiges, découvrit enfin une route.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="528">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And all roads lead to the abodes of men.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et les routes vont toutes chez les hommes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="529">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” he said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit-il.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="530">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He was standing before a garden, all a-bloom with roses.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’était un jardin fleuri de roses.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="531">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” said the roses.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dirent les roses.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="532">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince gazed at them.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince les regarda.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="533">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They all looked like his flower.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elles ressemblaient toutes à sa fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="10-9" id="534">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Who are you?”<br/>he demanded, thunderstruck.<br/>"We are roses,” the roses said.<br/>And he was overcome with sadness.<br/>His flower had told him that<br/>she was the only one of her kind in all the universe.<br/>And here were five thousand of them, all alike, in one single garden!<br/>"She would be very much annoyed,” he said to himself, "if she should see that... she would cough<br/>most dreadfully, and she would pretend that she was dying, to avoid being laughed at.<br/>And I should be obliged to pretend that I was nursing her back to life, for if I did not do that, to humble myself also, she would really allow herself to die...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Qui êtes-vous ?<br/>leur demanda-t-il, stupéfait.<br/>– Nous sommes des roses, dirent les roses.<br/>– Ah ! fit le petit prince…<br/>Et il se sentit très malheureux.<br/>Sa fleur lui avait raconté qu’elle était seule de son espèce dans l’univers.<br/>Et voici qu’il en était cinq mille, toutes semblables, dans un seul jardin !<br/>' Elle serait bien vexée, se dit-il, si elle voyait ça… elle tousserait énormément et ferait semblant de mourir pour échapper au ridicule.<br/>Et je serais bien obligé de faire semblant de la soigner, car, sinon, pour m’humilier moi aussi, elle se laisserait vraiment mourir… '<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="535">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then he went on with his reflections: "I thought that I was rich, with a flower that was unique in all the world; and all I had was a common rose.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Puis il se dit encore : ' Je me croyais riche d’une fleur unique, et je ne possède qu’une rose ordinaire.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="536">
  <src xml:lang="EN">A common rose, and three volcanoes that come up to my knees— and one of them perhaps extinct forever... that doesn’t make me a very great prince...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça et mes trois volcans qui m’arrivent au genou, et dont l’un, peut-être, est éteint pour toujours, ça ne fait pas de moi un bien grand prince… ' Et, couché dans l’herbe, il pleura.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="537">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he lay down in the grass and cried.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est alors qu’apparut le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="538">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was then that the fox appeared.<br/>"Good morning,” said the fox.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit le renard.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="539">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” the little prince responded politely, although when he turned around he saw</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, répondit poliment le petit prince, qui se retourna mais ne vit rien.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="540">
  <src xml:lang="EN">nothing. "I am right here,” the voice said, "under the apple tree.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je suis là, dit la voix, sous le pommier.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-4" id="541">
  <src xml:lang="EN">" Who are you?”<br/>asked the little prince, and added, "You are very pretty to look at.”<br/>"I am a fox,” said the fox.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Qui es-tu ?<br/>dit le petit prince.<br/>Tu es bien joli…<br/>– Je suis un renard, dit le renard.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="542">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Come and play with me,” proposed the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Viens jouer avec moi, lui proposa le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="22-20" id="543">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I am so unhappy.”<br/>"I cannot play with you,” the fox said.<br/>"I am not tamed.”<br/>"Ah! Please excuse me,” said the little prince.<br/>But, after some thought, he added: "What does<br/>that mean, ‘tame’?”<br/>"You do not live here,” said the fox.<br/>"What is it that you are looking for?”<br/>"I am looking for men,” said the little prince.<br/>"What does that mean, ‘tame’?”<br/>"Men,” said the fox.<br/>"They have guns, and they hunt.<br/>It is very disturbing.<br/>They also raise<br/>chickens. These are their only interests.<br/>Are you looking for chickens?”<br/>"No,” said the little prince.<br/>"I am looking for friends.<br/>What does that mean, ‘tame’?”<br/>"It is an act too often neglected,” said the fox.<br/>It means to establish ties.”<br/>"‘To establish ties’?”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je suis tellement triste…<br/>– Je ne puis pas jouer avec toi, dit le renard.<br/>Je ne suis pas apprivoisé.<br/>– Ah ! pardon, fit le petit prince.<br/>Mais, après réflexion, il ajouta :<br/>– Qu’est-ce que signifie ' apprivoiser ' ?<br/>– Tu n’es pas d’ici, dit le renard, que cherches-tu ?<br/>– Je cherche les hommes, dit le petit prince.<br/>Qu’est-ce que signifie ' apprivoiser ' ?<br/>– Les hommes, dit le renard, ils ont des fusils et ils chassent.<br/>C’est bien gênant !<br/>Ils élèvent aussi des poules.<br/>C’est leur seul intérêt.<br/>Tu cherches des poules ?<br/>– Non, dit le petit prince.<br/>Je cherche des amis.<br/>Qu’est-ce que signifie ' apprivoiser ' ?<br/>– C’est une chose trop oubliée, dit le renard.<br/>Ça signifie ' créer des liens… '<br/>– Créer des liens ?<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="544">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Just that,” said the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr, dit le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="545">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"To me, you are still nothing more than a little boy who is just like a hundred thousand other little boys.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu n’es encore pour moi qu’un petit garçon tout semblable à cent mille petits garçons.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="546">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And I have no need of you.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et je n’ai pas besoin de toi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="547">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And you, on your part, have no need of me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et tu n’as pas besoin de moi non plus.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="548">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To you, I am nothing more than a fox like a hundred thousand other foxes.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je ne suis pour toi qu’un renard semblable à cent mille renards.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="549">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But if you tame me, then we shall need each other.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais, si tu m’apprivoises, nous aurons besoin l’un de l’autre.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="550">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To me, you will be unique in all the world.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu seras pour moi unique au monde.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="551">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To you, I shall be unique in all the world...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je serai pour toi unique au monde…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="552">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I am beginning to understand,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je commence à comprendre, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="553">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"There is a flower...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il y a une fleur… je crois qu’elle m’a apprivoisé…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="554">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I think that she has tamed me...”<br/>"It is possible,” said the fox.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est possible, dit le renard.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="555">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"On the Earth one sees all sorts of things.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On voit sur la Terre toutes sortes de choses…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-3" id="556">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Oh, but this is not on the Earth!”<br/>said the little prince.<br/>The fox seemed perplexed, and very curious.<br/>"On another planet?”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Oh ! ce n’est pas sur la Terre, dit le petit prince.<br/>Le renard parut très intrigué :<br/>– Sur une autre planète ?<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="557">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Oui.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="558">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Are there hunters on this planet?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Il y a des chasseurs, sur cette planète-là ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="559">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"No.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Non.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="560">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah, that is interesting!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ça, c’est intéressant !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="561">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Are there chickens?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et des poules ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="562">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"No.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Non.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="563">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Nothing is perfect,” sighed the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Rien n’est parfait, soupira le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="564">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he came back to his idea.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais le renard revint à son idée :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="565">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"My life is very monotonous,” the fox said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ma vie est monotone.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="10-11" id="566">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I hunt chickens; men hunt me.<br/>All the chickens are just alike, and all the men are just alike.<br/>And, in consequence, I am a little bored.<br/>But if you tame me, it will be as if the sun came to shine on my life.<br/>I shall know the sound of a step that will be different from all the others.<br/>Other steps send me hurrying back underneath the ground.<br/>Yours will call me, like music, out of my burrow.<br/>And then look: you see the grain-fields down yonder?<br/>I do not eat bread.<br/>Wheat is of no use to me.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je chasse les poules, les hommes me chassent.<br/>Toutes les poules se ressemblent, et tous les hommes se ressemblent.<br/>Je m’ennuie donc un peu.<br/>Mais, si tu m’apprivoises, ma vie sera comme ensoleillée.<br/>Je connaîtrai un bruit de pas qui sera différent de tous les autres.<br/>Les autres pas me font rentrer sous terre.<br/>Le tien m’appellera hors du terrier, comme une musique.<br/>Et puis regarde !<br/>Tu vois, là-bas, les champs de blé ?<br/>Je ne mange pas de pain.<br/>Le blé pour moi est inutile.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="567">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The wheat fields have nothing to say to me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les champs de blé ne me rappellent rien.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="8-7" id="568">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And that is sad.<br/>But you have hair that is the colour of gold.<br/>Think how wonderful that will be when you have tamed me!<br/>The grain, which is also golden, will bring me back the thought of you.<br/>And I shall love to listen to the wind in the wheat...”<br/>The fox gazed at the little prince, for a long time.<br/>"Please, tame me!”<br/>he said.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et ça, c’est triste !<br/>Mais tu as des cheveux couleur d’or.<br/>Alors ce sera merveilleux quand tu m’auras apprivoisé !<br/>Le blé, qui est doré, me fera souvenir de toi.<br/>Et j’aimerai le bruit du vent dans le blé… Le renard se tut et regarda longtemps le petit prince :<br/>– S’il te plaît… apprivoise-moi !<br/>dit-il.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="569">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I want to, very much,” the little prince replied.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je veux bien, répondit le petit prince, mais je n’ai pas beaucoup de temps.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="570">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But I have not much time.<br/>I have friends to discover, and a great many things to understand.”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai des amis à découvrir et beaucoup de choses à connaître.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="571">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"One only understands the things that one tames,” said the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– On ne connaît que les choses que l’on apprivoise, dit le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="572">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Men have no more time to understand anything.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les hommes n’ont plus le temps de rien connaître.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="573">
  <src xml:lang="EN">They buy things all ready-made at the shops.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ils achètent des choses toutes faites chez les marchands.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="574">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But there is no shop anywhere where one can buy friendship, and so men have no friends any more.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais comme il n’existe point de marchands d’amis, les hommes n’ont plus d’amis.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="575">
  <src xml:lang="EN">If you want a friend, tame me...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Si tu veux un ami, apprivoise-moi !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="576">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What must I do, to tame you?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Que faut-il faire ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="577">
  <src xml:lang="EN">asked the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="578">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"You must be very patient,” replied the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Il faut être très patient, répondit le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="579">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"First you will sit down at a little distance from me, like that, in the grass.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu t’assoiras d’abord un peu loin de moi, comme ça, dans l’herbe.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="580">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I shall look at you out of the corner of my eye, and you will say nothing.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je te regarderai du coin de l’oeil et tu ne diras rien.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="581">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Words are the source of misunderstandings.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le langage est source de malentendus.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="582">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But you will sit a little closer to me, every day...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais, chaque jour, tu pourras t’asseoir un peu plus près…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="583">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The next day the little prince came back.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le lendemain revint le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="584">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It would have been better to come back at the same hour,” said the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Il eût mieux valu revenir à la même heure, dit le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="585">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"If, for example, you come at four o’clock in the afternoon, then at three o’clock I shall begin to be happy.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Si tu viens, par exemple, à quatre heures de l’après-midi, dès trois heures je commencerai d’être heureux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="586">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I shall feel happier and happier as the hour advances.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Plus l’heure avancera, plus je me sentirai heureux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="587">
  <src xml:lang="EN">At four o’clock, I shall already be worrying and jumping about.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">À quatre heures, déjà, je m’agiterai et m’inquiéterai ; je découvrirai le prix du bonheur !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-2" id="588">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I shall show you how happy I am!<br/>But if you come at just any time, I shall never know at what hour my heart is to be ready to greet you...<br/>One must observe the proper rites...”<br/>"What is a rite?”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais si tu viens n’importe quand, je ne saurai jamais à quelle heure m’habiller le coeur… Il faut des rites.<br/>– Qu’est-ce qu’un rite ?<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="589">
  <src xml:lang="EN">asked the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="590">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Those also are actions too often neglected,” said the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est aussi quelque chose de trop oublié, dit le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="591">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"They are what make one day different from other days, one hour from other hours.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est ce qui fait qu’un jour est différent des autres jours, une heure, des autres heures.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="592">
  <src xml:lang="EN">There is a rite, for example, among my hunters.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il y a un rite, par exemple, chez mes chasseurs.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="593">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Every Thursday they dance with the village girls.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ils dansent le jeudi avec les filles du village.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="594">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So Thursday is a wonderful day for me!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors le jeudi est jour merveilleux !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="595">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I can take a walk as far as the vineyards.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je vais me promener jusqu’à la vigne.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="596">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But if the hunters danced at just any time, every day would be like every other day, and I should never have any vacation at all.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Si les chasseurs dansaient n’importe quand, les jours se ressembleraient tous, et je n’aurais point de vacances.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="597">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So the little prince tamed the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ainsi le petit prince apprivoisa le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="598">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And when the hour of his departure drew near...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et quand l’heure du départ fut proche :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="599">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah,” said the fox, "I shall cry.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! dit le renard… Je pleurerai.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="600">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is your own fault,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est ta faute, dit le petit prince, je ne te souhaitais point de mal, mais tu as voulu que je t’apprivoise…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="601">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I never wished you any sort of harm; but you wanted me to tame you...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr, dit le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="602">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, that is so,” said the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais tu vas pleurer !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="603">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"But now you are going to cry!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="604">
  <src xml:lang="EN">said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr, dit le renard.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="605">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, that is so,” said the fox.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Alors tu n’y gagnes rien !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="606">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Then it has done you no good at all!”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– J’y gagne, dit le renard, à cause de la couleur du blé.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="607">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It has done me good,” said the fox, "because of the colour of the wheat fields.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Puis il ajouta :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="608">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And then he added: "Go and look again at the roses.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Va revoir les roses.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="609">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You will understand now that yours is unique in all the world.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu comprendras que la tienne est unique au monde.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="610">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then come back to say goodbye to me, and I will make you a present of a secret.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu reviendras me dire adieu, et je te ferai cadeau d’un secret.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="611">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince went away, to look again at the roses.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince s’en fut revoir les roses.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="612">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"You are not at all like my rose,” he said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Vous n’êtes pas du tout semblables à ma rose, vous n’êtes rien encore, leur dit-il.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="22-27" id="613">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"As yet you are nothing.<br/>No one has tamed you, and you have tamed no one.<br/>You are like my fox when I first knew him.<br/>He was only a fox like a hundred thousand other foxes.<br/>But I have made him my friend, and now he is unique in all the world.”<br/>And the roses were very much embarrassed.<br/>"You are beautiful, but you are empty,” he went on.<br/>"One could not die for you.<br/>To be sure, an ordinary passer-by would think that my rose looked just like you, the rose that belongs to me.<br/>But in herself alone she is more important than all the hundreds of you other roses: because it is she that I have watered; because it is she that I have put under the glass globe; because it is she that I have sheltered behind the screen; because it is for her that I have killed the caterpillars (except the two or three that we saved to become butterflies); because it is she that I have listened to, when she grumbled, or boasted, or even sometimes when she said nothing.<br/>Because she is my rose.<br/>And he went back to meet the fox.<br/>"Goodbye,” he said.<br/>"Goodbye,” said the fox.<br/>"And now here is my secret, a very simple secret: It is only with the heart that one can see rightly; what is essential is invisible to the eye.”<br/>"What is essential is invisible to the eye,” the little prince repeated, so that he would be sure to remember.<br/>"It is the time you have wasted for your rose that makes your rose so important.”<br/>"It is the time I have wasted for my rose...” said the little prince, so that he would be sure to remember.<br/>"Men have forgotten this truth,” said the fox.<br/>"But you must not forget it.<br/>You become responsible, forever, for what you have tamed.<br/>You are responsible for your rose...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Personne ne vous a apprivoisées et vous n’avez apprivoisé personne.<br/>Vous êtes comme était mon renard.<br/>Ce n’était qu’un renard semblable à cent mille autres.<br/>Mais j’en ai fait mon ami, et il est maintenant unique au monde.<br/>Et les roses étaient bien gênées.<br/>– Vous êtes belles, mais vous êtes vides, leur dit-il encore.<br/>On ne peut pas mourir pour vous.<br/>Bien sûr, ma rose à moi, un passant ordinaire croirait qu’elle vous ressemble.<br/>Mais à elle seule elle est plus importante que vous toutes, puisque c’est elle que j’ai arrosée.<br/>Puisque c’est elle que j’ai mise sous globe.<br/>Puisque c’est elle que j’ai abritée par le paravent.<br/>Puisque c’est elle dont j’ai tué les chenilles (sauf les deux ou trois pour les papillons).<br/>Puisque c’est elle que j’ai écoutée se plaindre, ou se vanter, ou même quelquefois se taire.<br/>Puisque c’est ma rose.<br/>Et il revint vers le renard :<br/>– Adieu, dit-il…<br/>– Adieu, dit le renard.<br/>Voici mon secret.<br/>Il est très simple : on ne voit bien qu’avec le coeur.<br/>L’essentiel est invisible pour les yeux.<br/>– L’essentiel est invisible pour les yeux, répéta le petit prince, afin de se souvenir.<br/>– C’est le temps que tu as perdu pour ta rose qui fait ta rose si importante.<br/>– C’est le temps que j’ai perdu pour ma rose… fit le petit prince, afin de se souvenir.<br/>– Les hommes ont oublié cette vérité, dit le renard.<br/>Mais tu ne dois pas l’oublier.<br/>Tu deviens responsable pour toujours de ce que tu as apprivoisé.<br/>Tu es responsable de ta rose…<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="614">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I am responsible for my rose,” the little prince repeated, so that he would be sure to remember.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je suis responsable de ma rose… répéta le petit prince, afin de se souvenir.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="615">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="616">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Good morning,” said the railway switchman.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bonjour, dit l’aiguilleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="617">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What do you do here?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Que fais-tu ici ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="618">
  <src xml:lang="EN">the little prince asked.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="619">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I sort out travellers, in bundles of a thousand,” said the switchman.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Je trie les voyageurs, par paquets de mille, dit l’aiguilleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="620">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I send off the trains that carry them; now to the right, now to the left.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’expédie les trains qui les emportent, tantôt vers la droite, tantôt vers la gauche.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="621">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And a brilliantly lighted express train shook the switchman’s cabin as it rushed by with a roar like thunder.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et un rapide illuminé, grondant comme le tonnerre, fit trembler la cabine d’aiguillage.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="622">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"They are in a great hurry,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ils sont bien pressés, dit le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="623">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What are they looking for?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Que cherchent- ils ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="624">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Not even the locomotive engineer knows that,” said the switchman.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– L’homme de la locomotive l’ignore lui-même, dit l’aiguilleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="625">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And a second brilliantly lighted express thundered by, in the opposite direction.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et gronda, en sens inverse, un second rapide illuminé.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="626">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Are they coming back already?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ils reviennent déjà ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="627">
  <src xml:lang="EN">demanded the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">demanda le petit prince…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="628">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"These are not the same ones,” said</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce ne sont pas les mêmes, dit l’aiguilleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="8-5" id="629">
  <src xml:lang="EN">the switchman.<br/>"It is an exchange.”<br/>"Were they not satisfied where they were?”<br/>asked the little prince.<br/>"No one is ever satisfied where he is,” said the switchman.<br/>And they heard the roaring thunder of<br/>a third brilliantly lighted express.<br/>"Are they pursuing the first travellers?”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est un échange.<br/>– Ils n’étaient pas contents, là où ils étaient ?<br/>– On n’est jamais content là où l’on est, dit l’aiguilleur.<br/>Et gronda le tonnerre d’un troisième rapide illuminé.<br/>– Ils poursuivent les premiers voyageurs ?<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="630">
  <src xml:lang="EN">demanded the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">demanda le petit prince.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="631">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"They are pursuing nothing at all,” said the switchman.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ils ne poursuivent rien du tout, dit l’aiguilleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="21-17" id="632">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"They are asleep in there, or if they are<br/>not asleep they are yawning.<br/>Only the children are flattening their noses against the windowpanes.”<br/>"Only the children know what they are looking for,” said the little prince.<br/>"They waste their time over a rag doll and it becomes very important to them; and if anybody takes it away from them, they cry...”<br/>"They are lucky,” the switchman said.<br/>"Good morning,” said the little prince.<br/>"Good morning,” said the merchant.<br/>This was a merchant who sold pills that had been invented to quench thirst.<br/>You need only swallow<br/>one pill a week, and you would feel no need of anything to drink.<br/>"Why are you selling those?”<br/>asked the little prince.<br/>"Because they save a tremendous amount of time,” said the merchant.<br/>"Computations have been made by experts.<br/>With these pills, you save fifty-three minutes in every week.”<br/>"And what do I do with those fifty-three minutes?”<br/>"Anything you like...”<br/>"As for me,” said the little prince to himself, "if I had fifty-three minutes to spend as I liked, I<br/>should walk at my leisure toward a spring of fresh water.”<br/>It was now the eighth day since I had had my accident in the desert, and I had listened to the story of the merchant as I was drinking the last drop of my water supply.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ils dorment là-dedans, ou bien ils bâillent.<br/>Les enfants seuls écrasent leur nez contre les vitres.<br/>– Les enfants seuls savent ce qu’ils cherchent, fit le petit prince.<br/>Ils perdent du temps pour une poupée de chiffons, et elle devient très importante, et si on la leur enlève, ils pleurent…<br/>– Ils ont de la chance, dit l’aiguilleur.<br/>– Bonjour, dit le petit prince.<br/>– Bonjour, dit le marchand.<br/>C’était un marchand de pilules perfectionnées qui apaisent la soif.<br/>On en avale une par semaine et l’on n’éprouve plus le besoin de boire.<br/>– Pourquoi vends-tu ça ?<br/>dit le petit prince.<br/>– C’est une grosse économie de temps, dit le marchand.<br/>Les experts ont fait des calculs.<br/>On épargne cinquante-trois minutes par semaine.<br/>– Et que fait-on de ces cinquante-trois minutes ?<br/>– On en fait ce que l’on veut… ' Moi, se dit le petit prince, si j’avais cinquante-trois minutes à dépenser, je marcherais tout doucement vers une fontaine… '<br/>Nous en étions au huitième jour de ma panne dans le désert, et j’avais écouté l’histoire du marchand en buvant la dernière goutte de ma provision d’eau :<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="633">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Ah,” I said to the little prince, "these memories of yours are very charming; but I have not yet</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ah ! dis-je au petit prince, ils sont bien jolis, tes souvenirs, mais je n’ai pas encore réparé mon avion, je n’ai plus rien à boire, et je serais heureux, moi aussi, si je pouvais marcher tout doucement vers une fontaine !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="9-7" id="634">
  <src xml:lang="EN">succeeded in repairing my plane; I have nothing more to drink; and I, too, should be very happy if I could walk at my leisure toward a spring of fresh water!”<br/>"My friend the fox...” the little prince said to me.<br/>"My dear little man, this is no longer a matter that has anything to do with the fox!”<br/>"Why not?”<br/>"Because I am about to die of thirst...”<br/>He did not follow my reasoning, and he answered me: "It is a good thing to have had a friend, even if one is about to die.<br/>I, for instance, am very glad to have had a fox as a friend...”<br/>"He has no way of guessing the danger,” I said to myself.<br/>"He has never been either hungry or<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mon ami le renard, me dit-il…<br/>– Mon petit bonhomme, il ne s’agit plus du renard !<br/>– Pourquoi ?<br/>– Parce qu’on va mourir de soif… Il ne comprit pas mon raisonnement, il me répondit :<br/>– C’est bien d’avoir eu un ami, même si l’on va mourir.<br/>Moi, je suis bien content d’avoir eu un ami renard… ' Il ne mesure pas le danger, me dis-je.<br/>Il n’a jamais ni faim ni soif.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="635">
  <src xml:lang="EN">thirsty. A little sunshine is all he needs...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Un peu de soleil lui suffit… '</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="636">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he looked at me steadily, and replied to my thought: "I am thirsty, too.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais il me regarda et répondit à ma pensée :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-4" id="637">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Let us look for a well...”<br/>I made a gesture of weariness.<br/>It is absurd to look for a well, at random, in the immensity of the desert.<br/>But nevertheless we started walking.<br/>When we had trudged along for several hours, in silence, the darkness fell, and the stars began to come out.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– J’ai soif aussi… cherchons un puits…<br/>J’eus un geste de lassitude : il est absurde de chercher un puits, au hasard, dans l’immensité du désert.<br/>Cependant nous nous mîmes en marche.<br/>Quand nous eûmes marché, des heures, en silence, la nuit tomba, et les étoiles commencèrent de s’éclairer.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="638">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Thirst had made me a little feverish, and I looked at them as if I were in a dream.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je les apercevais comme en rêve, ayant un peu de fièvre, à cause de ma soif.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="639">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince’s last words came reeling back into my memory: "Then you are thirsty, too?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les mots du petit prince dansaient dans ma mémoire :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="640">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I demanded. But he did not reply to my question.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Tu as donc soif, toi aussi ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="641">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He merely said to me: "Water may also be good for the heart...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">lui demandai-je.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="642">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I did not understand this answer, but I said nothing.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais il ne répondit pas à ma question.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="643">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I knew very well that it was impossible to cross-examine him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me dit simplement :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="644">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He was tired. He sat down. I sat down beside him.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– L’eau peut aussi être bonne pour le coeur… Je ne compris pas sa réponse mais je me tus… Je savais bien qu’il ne fallait pas l’interroger.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="645">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And, after a little silence, he spoke again: "The stars are beautiful, because of a flower that cannot be seen.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il était fatigué.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="646">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I replied, "Yes, that is so.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il s’assit. Je m’assis auprès de lui.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="647">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And, without saying anything more, I looked across the ridges of sand that were stretched out before us in the moonlight.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et, après un silence, il dit encore :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="648">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"The desert is beautiful,” the little prince added.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Les étoiles sont belles, à cause d’une fleur que l’on ne voit pas… Je répondis ' bien sûr ' et je regardai, sans parler, les plis du sable sous la lune.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="649">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And that was true.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Le désert est beau, ajouta-t-il… Et c’était vrai.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="650">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have always loved the desert.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’ai toujours aimé le désert.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="651">
  <src xml:lang="EN">One sits down on a desert sand dune, sees</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On s’assoit sur une dune de sable.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="652">
  <src xml:lang="EN">nothing, hears nothing.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On ne voit rien.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="653">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Yet through the silence something throbs, and gleams...<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">On n’entend rien.<br/>Et cependant quelque chose rayonne en silence…<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="654">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What makes the desert beautiful,” said the little prince, "is that somewhere it hides a well...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce qui embellit le désert, dit le petit prince, c’est qu’il cache un puits quelque part…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="655">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I was astonished by a sudden understanding of that mysterious radiation of the sands.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je fus surpris de comprendre soudain ce mystérieux rayonnement du sable.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="656">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When I was a little boy I lived in an old house, and legend told us that a treasure was buried there.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Lorsque j’étais petit garçon j’habitais une maison ancienne, et la légende racontait qu’un trésor y était enfoui.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="657">
  <src xml:lang="EN">To be sure, no one had ever known how to find it; perhaps no one had ever even looked for it.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Bien sûr, jamais personne n’a su le découvrir, ni peut- être même ne l’a cherché.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="12-9" id="658">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But it cast an enchantment over that house.<br/>My home was hiding a secret in the depths of its heart...<br/>"Yes,” I said to the little prince.<br/>"The house, the stars, the desert— what gives them their beauty is something that is invisible!”<br/>"I am glad,” he said, "that you agree with my fox.”<br/>As the little prince dropped off to sleep, I took him in my arms and set out walking once more.<br/>I felt deeply moved, and stirred.<br/>It seemed to me that I was carrying a very fragile treasure.<br/>It seemed to me, even, that there was nothing more fragile on all Earth.<br/>In the moonlight I looked at his pale forehead, his closed eyes, his locks of hair that trembled in the wind, and I said to myself:<br/>"What I see here is nothing but a shell.<br/>What is most important is invisible...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais il enchantait toute cette maison.<br/>Ma maison cachait un secret au fond de son coeur…<br/>– Oui, dis-je au petit prince, qu’il s’agisse de la maison, des étoiles ou du désert, ce qui fait leur beauté est invisible !<br/>– Je suis content, dit-il, que tu sois d’accord avec mon renard.<br/>Comme le petit prince s’endormait, je le pris dans mes bras, et me remis en route.<br/>J’étais ému. Il me semblait porter un trésor fragile.<br/>Il me semblait même qu’il n’y eût rien de plus fragile sur la Terre.<br/>Je regardais, à la lumière de la lune, ce front pâle, ces yeux clos, ces mèches de cheveux qui tremblaient au vent, et je me disais : ' Ce que je vois là n’est qu’une écorce.<br/>Le plus important est invisible… '<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="659">
  <src xml:lang="EN">As his lips opened slightly with the suspicious of a half-smile, I said to myself, again: "What moves me so deeply, about this little prince who is sleeping here, is his loyalty to a flower— the image of a rose that shines through his whole being like the flame of a lamp, even when he is asleep...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Comme ses lèvres entr’ouvertes ébauchaient un demi- sourire je me dis encore : ' Ce qui m’émeut si fort de ce petit prince endormi, c’est sa fidélité pour une fleur, c’est l’image d’une rose qui rayonne en lui comme la flamme d’une lampe, même quand il dort… ' Et je le devinai plus fragile encore.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-2" id="660">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And I felt him to be more fragile still.<br/>I felt the need of protecting him, as if he himself were a flame that might be extinguished by a little puff of wind...<br/>And, as I walked on so, I found the well, at daybreak.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il faut bien protéger les lampes : un coup de vent peut les éteindre…<br/>Et, marchant ainsi, je découvris le puits au lever du jour.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="661">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Men,” said the little prince, "set out on their way in express trains, but they do not know what they are looking for.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Les hommes, dit le petit prince, ils s’enfournent dans les rapides, mais ils ne savent plus ce qu’ils cherchent.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="662">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then they rush about, and get excited, and turn round and round...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors ils s’agitent et tournent en rond… Et il ajouta :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="17-11" id="663">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he added: "It is not worth the trouble...”<br/>The well that we had come to was not like the wells of the Sahara.<br/>The wells of the Sahara are mere holes dug in the sand.<br/>This one was like a well in a village.<br/>But there was no village here, and I thought I must be dreaming...<br/>"It is strange,” I said to the little prince.<br/>"Everything is ready for use: the pulley, the bucket, the rope...”<br/>He laughed, touched the rope, and set the pulley to working.<br/>And the pulley moaned, like an old weathervane, which the wind has long since forgotten.<br/>"Do you hear?”<br/>said the little prince.<br/>"We have wakened the well, and it is singing...”<br/>I did not want him to tire himself with the rope.<br/>"Leave it to me,” I said.<br/>"It is too heavy for you.”<br/>I hoisted the bucket slowly to the edge of the well and set it there, happy, tired as I was, over my achievement.<br/>The song of the pulley was still in my ears, and I could see the sunlight shimmer in the still trembling water.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce n’est pas la peine… Le puits que nous avions atteint ne ressemblait pas aux puits sahariens.<br/>Les puits sahariens sont de simples trous creusés dans le sable.<br/>Celui-là ressemblait à un puits de village.<br/>Mais il n’y avait là aucun village, et je croyais rêver.<br/>– C’est étrange, dis-je au petit prince, tout est prêt : la poulie, le seau et la corde… Il rit, toucha la corde, fit jouer la poulie.<br/>Et la poulie gémit comme gémit une vieille girouette quand le vent a longtemps dormi.<br/>– Tu entends, dit le petit prince, nous réveillons ce puits et il chante… Je ne voulais pas qu’il fît un effort :<br/>– Laisse-moi faire, lui dis-je, c’est trop lourd pour toi.<br/>Lentement je hissai le seau jusqu’à la margelle.<br/>Je l’y installai bien d’aplomb.<br/>Dans mes oreilles durait le chant de la poulie et, dans l’eau qui tremblait encore, je voyais trembler le soleil.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="664">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I am thirsty for this water,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– J’ai soif de cette eau-là, dit le petit prince, donne-moi à boire… Et je compris ce qu’il avait cherché !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-2" id="665">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Give me some of it to drink...”<br/>And I understood what he had been looking for.<br/>I raised the bucket to his lips.<br/>He drank, his eyes closed.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je soulevai le seau jusqu’à ses lèvres.<br/>Il but, les yeux fermés.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="666">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was as sweet as some special festival treat.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’était doux comme une fête.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-3" id="667">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This water was indeed a different thing from ordinary nourishment.<br/>Its sweetness was born of the walk under the stars, the song of the pulley, the effort of my arms.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Cette eau était bien autre<br/>chose qu’un aliment.<br/>Elle était née de la marche sous les étoiles, du chant de la poulie, de l’effort de mes bras.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="668">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was good for the heart, like a present.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Elle était bonne pour le coeur, comme un cadeau.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="669">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When I was a little boy, the lights of the Christmas tree, the music of the Midnight Mass, the tenderness of smiling faces, used to make up, so, the radiance of the gifts I received.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Lorsque j’étais petit garçon, la lumière de l’arbre de Noël, la musique de la messe de minuit, la douceur des sourires faisaient ainsi tout le rayonnement du cadeau de Noël que je recevais.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="670">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"The men where you live,” said the little prince, "raise five thousand roses in the same garden and they do not find in it what they are looking for.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Les hommes de chez toi, dit le petit prince, cultivent cinq mille roses dans un même jardin… et ils n’y trouvent pas ce qu’ils cherchent…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="671">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"They do not find it,” I replied.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ils ne le trouvent pas, répondis-je…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="672">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"And yet what they are looking for could be found in one single rose, or in a little water.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Et cependant ce qu’ils cherchent pourrait être trouvé dans une seule rose ou un peu d’eau…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="673">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, that is true,” I said.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr, répondis-je.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="674">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And the little prince added: "But the eyes are blind.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et le petit prince ajouta :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="675">
  <src xml:lang="EN">One must look with the heart...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Mais les yeux sont aveugles.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="676">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I had drunk the water.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il faut chercher avec le coeur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="677">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I breathed easily.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’avais bu. Je respirais bien.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="678">
  <src xml:lang="EN">At sunrise the sand is the colour of honey.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le sable, au lever du jour, est couleur de miel.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="679">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And that honey colour was making me happy, too.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’étais heureux aussi de cette couleur de miel.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="680">
  <src xml:lang="EN">What brought me, then, this sense of grief?</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Pourquoi fallait-il que j’eusse de la peine…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="681">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"You must keep your promise,” said the little prince, softly, as he sat down beside me once more.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Il faut que tu tiennes ta promesse, me dit doucement le petit prince, qui, de nouveau, s’était assis auprès de moi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="682">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What promise?”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Quelle promesse ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="683">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"You know, a muzzle for my sheep...<br/>I am responsible for this flower...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Tu sais… une muselière pour mon mouton… je suis responsable de cette fleur !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="684">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I took my rough drafts of drawings out of my pocket.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je sortis de ma poche mes ébauches de dessin.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="685">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince looked them over, and laughed as he said:</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince les aperçut et dit en riant :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="686">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Your baobabs, they look a little like cabbages.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Tes baobabs, ils ressemblent un peu à des choux…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="687">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Oh!” I had been so proud of my baobabs!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Oh! Moi qui étais si fier des baobabs !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="688">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Your fox, his ears look a little like horns; and they are too long.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ton renard… ses oreilles… elles ressemblent un peu à des cornes… et elles sont trop longues !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="29-26" id="689">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he laughed again.<br/>"You are not fair, little prince,” I said.<br/>"I don’t know how to draw anything except boa constrictors from the outside and boa constrictors from the inside.”<br/>"Oh, that will be all right,” he said, "children understand.”<br/>So then I made a pencil sketch of a muzzle.<br/>And as I gave it to him my heart was torn.<br/>"You have plans that I do not know about,” I said.<br/>But he did not answer me.<br/>He said to me, instead: "You know, my descent to the earth...<br/>Tomorrow will be its anniversary.”<br/>Then, after a silence, he went on: "I came down very near here.”<br/>And he flushed.<br/>And once again, without understanding why, I had a queer sense of sorrow.<br/>One question, however, occurred to me: "Then it was not by chance that on the morning when I first met you— a week ago— you were strolling along like that, all alone, a thousand miles from any inhabited region?<br/>You were on the your way back to the place where you landed?”<br/>The little prince flushed again.<br/>And I added, with some hesitancy: "Perhaps it was because of the anniversary?”<br/>The little prince flushed once more.<br/>He never answered questions, but when one flushes does that not mean "Yes”?<br/>"Ah,” I said to him, "I am a little frightened...”<br/>But he interrupted me.<br/>"Now you must work.<br/>You must return to your engine.<br/>I will be waiting for you here.<br/>Come back tomorrow evening...”<br/>But I was not reassured.<br/>I remembered the fox.<br/>One runs the risk of weeping a little, if one lets himself be tamed...<br/>Beside the well there was the ruin of an old stone wall.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et il rit encore.<br/>– Tu es injuste, petit bonhomme, je ne savais rien dessiner que les boas fermés et les boas ouverts.<br/>– Oh ! ça ira, dit-il, les enfants savent.<br/>Je crayonnai donc une muselière.<br/>Et j’eus le coeur serré en la lui donnant :<br/>– Tu as des projets que j’ignore… Mais il ne me répondit pas.<br/>Il me dit :<br/>– Tu sais, ma chute sur la Terre… c’en sera demain l’anniversaire… Puis, après un silence il dit encore :<br/>– J’étais tombé tout près d’ici… Et il rougit.<br/>Et de nouveau, sans comprendre pourquoi, j’éprouvai un chagrin bizarre.<br/>Cependant une question me vint :<br/>– Alors ce n’est pas par hasard que, le matin où je t’ai connu, il y a huit jours, tu te promenais comme ça, tout seul, à mille milles de toutes les régions habitées !<br/>Tu retournais vers le point de ta chute ?<br/>Le petit prince rougit encore.<br/>Et j’ajoutai, en hésitant :<br/>– À cause, peut-être, de l’anniversaire ?<br/>… Le petit prince rougit de nouveau.<br/>Il ne répondait jamais aux questions, mais, quand on rougit, ça signifie ' oui ', n’estce pas ?<br/>– Ah ! lui dis-je, j’ai peur… Mais il me répondit :<br/>– Tu dois maintenant travailler.<br/>Tu dois repartir vers ta machine.<br/>Je t’attends ici.<br/>Reviens demain soir… Mais je n’étais pas rassuré.<br/>Je me souvenais du renard.<br/>On risque de pleurer un peu si l’on s’est laissé apprivoiser…<br/>Il y avait, à côté du puits, une ruine de vieux mur de pierre.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="690">
  <src xml:lang="EN">When I came back from my work, the next evening, I saw from some distance away my little prince sitting on top of a wall, with his feet dangling.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Lorsque je revins de mon travail, le lendemain soir, j’aperçus de loin mon petit prince assis là-haut, les jambes pendantes.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-4" id="691">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And I heard him say: "Then you don’t remember.<br/>This is not the exact spot.”<br/>Another voice must have answered him, for he replied to it: "Yes, yes!<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et je l’entendis qui parlait :<br/>– Tu ne t’en souviens donc pas ?<br/>disait-il. Ce n’est pas tout à fait ici !<br/>Une autre voix lui répondit sans doute, puisqu’il répliqua :<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="692">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is the right day, but this is not the place.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Si ! Si ! c’est bien le jour, mais ce n’est pas ici l’endroit… Je poursuivis ma marche vers le mur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="9-10" id="693">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I continued my walk toward the wall.<br/>At no time did I see or hear anyone.<br/>The little prince, however, replied once again: "...<br/>Exactly. You will see where my track begins, in the sand.<br/>You have nothing to do but wait for me there.<br/>I shall be there tonight.”<br/>I was only twenty metres from the wall, and I still saw nothing.<br/>After a silence the little prince spoke again: "You have good poison?<br/>You are sure that it will not make me suffer too long?”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je ne voyais ni n’entendais toujours personne.<br/>Pourtant le petit prince répliqua de nouveau :<br/>– … Bien sûr.<br/>Tu verras où commence ma trace dans le sable.<br/>Tu n’as qu’à m’y attendre.<br/>J’y serai cette nuit.<br/>J’étais à vingt mètres du mur et je ne voyais toujours rien.<br/>Le petit prince dit encore, après un silence :<br/>– Tu as du bon venin ?<br/>Tu es sûr de ne pas me faire souffrir longtemps ?<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="694">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I stopped in my tracks, my heart torn asunder; but still I did not understand.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je fis halte, le coeur serré, mais je ne comprenais toujours pas.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="695">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Now go away,” said the little prince.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Maintenant va-t’en, dit-il… je veux redescendre !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-3" id="696">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I want to get down from the wall.”<br/>I dropped my eyes, then, to the foot of the wall... and I leaped into the air.<br/>There before me, facing the little prince, was one of those yellow snakes that take just thirty seconds to bring your life to an end.<br/>Even as I was digging into my pocked to get out my revolver I made a running step back.<br/>But, at the noise I made, the snake let himself flow easily across the sand like the dying spray of a fountain, and, in no apparent hurry, disappeared, with a light metallic sound, among the stones.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors j’abaissai moi-même les yeux vers le pied du mur, et je fis un bond !<br/>Il était là, dressé vers le petit prince, un de ces serpents jaunes qui vous exécutent en trente secondes.<br/>Tout en fouillant ma poche pour en tirer mon revolver, je pris le pas de course, mais, au bruit que je fis, le serpent se laissa doucement couler dans le sable, comme un jet d’eau qui meurt, et, sans trop se presser, se faufila entre les pierres avec un léger bruit de métal.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="697">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I reached the wall just in time to catch my little man in my arms; his face was white as snow.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je parvins au mur juste à temps pour y recevoir dans les bras mon petit bonhomme de prince, pâle comme la neige.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="11-12" id="698">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"What does this mean?”<br/>I demanded. "Why are you talking with snakes?”<br/>I had loosened the golden muffler that he always wore.<br/>I had moistened his temples, and had given him some water to drink.<br/>And now I did not dare ask him any more questions.<br/>He looked at me very gravely, and put his arms around my neck.<br/>I felt his heart beating like the heart of a dying bird, shot with someone’s rifle...<br/>"I am glad that you have found what was the matter with your engine,” he said.<br/>"Now you can go back home”<br/>"How do you know about that?”<br/>I was just coming to tell him that my work had been successful, beyond anything that I had dared to hope.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Quelle est cette histoire-là !<br/>Tu parles maintenant avec les serpents !<br/>J’avais défait son éternel cache-nez d’or.<br/>Je lui avais mouillé les tempes et l’avais fait boire.<br/>Et maintenant je n’osais plus rien lui demander.<br/>Il me regarda gravement et m’entoura le cou de ses bras.<br/>Je sentais battre son coeur comme celui d’un oiseau qui meurt, quand on l’a tiré à la carabine.<br/>Il me dit :<br/>– Je suis content que tu aies trouvé ce qui manquait à ta machine.<br/>Tu vas pouvoir rentrer chez toi…<br/>– Comment sais-tu !<br/>Je venais justement lui annoncer que, contre toute espérance, j’avais réussi mon travail !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="699">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He made no answer to my question, but he added: "I, too, am going back home today...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il ne répondit rien à ma question, mais il ajouta :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="700">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then, sadly, "It is much farther... it is much more difficult...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Moi aussi, aujourd’hui, je rentre chez moi… Puis, mélancolique :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="701">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I realised clearly that something extraordinary was happening.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est bien plus loin… c’est bien plus difficile… Je sentais bien qu’il se passait quelque chose d’extraordinaire.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="702">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I was holding him close in my arms as if he were a little child; and yet it seemed to me that he was rushing headlong toward an abyss from which I could do nothing to restrain him...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je le serrais dans les bras comme un petit enfant, et cependant il me semblait qu’il coulait verticalement dans un abîme sans que je pusse rien pour le retenir…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="703">
  <src xml:lang="EN">His look was very serious, like some one lost far away.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il avait le regard sérieux, perdu très loin :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="704">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"I have your sheep.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– J’ai ton mouton.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="4-3" id="705">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And I have the sheep’s box.<br/>And I have the muzzle...”<br/>And he gave me a sad smile.<br/>I waited a long time.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et j’ai la caisse pour le mouton.<br/>Et j’ai la muselière… Et il sourit avec mélancolie.<br/>J’attendis longtemps.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="706">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I could see that he was reviving little by little.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Je sentais qu’il se réchauffait peu à peu :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="7-5" id="707">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Dear little man,” I said to him, "you are afraid...”<br/>He was afraid, there was no doubt about that.<br/>But he laughed lightly.<br/>"I shall be much more afraid this evening...”<br/>Once again I felt myself frozen by the sense of something irreparable.<br/>And I knew that I could not bear the thought of never hearing that laughter any more.<br/>For me, it was like a spring of fresh water in the desert.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Petit bonhomme, tu as eu peur… Il avait eu peur, bien sûr !<br/>Mais il rit doucement :<br/>– J’aurai bien plus peur ce soir… De nouveau je me sentis glacé par le sentiment de l’irréparable.<br/>Et je compris que je ne supportais pas l’idée de ne plus jamais entendre ce rire.<br/>C’était pour moi comme une fontaine dans le désert.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="708">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Little man,” I said, "I want to hear you laugh again.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Petit bonhomme, je veux encore t’entendre rire… Mais il me dit :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="709">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he said to me: "Tonight, it will be a year... my star, then, can be found right above the place where I came to the Earth, a year ago...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Cette nuit, ça fera un an.<br/>Mon étoile se trouvera juste au- dessus de l’endroit où je suis tombé l’année dernière…<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="710">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Little man,” I said, "tell me that it is only a bad dream, this affair of the snake, and the meeting- place, and the star...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Petit bonhomme, n’est-ce pas que c’est un mauvais rêve cette histoire de serpent et de rendez-vous et d’étoile… Mais il ne répondit pas à ma question.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="711">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he did not answer my plea.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il me dit :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="712">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He said to me, instead: "The thing that is important is the thing that is not seen...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce qui est important, ça ne se voit pas…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="713">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, I know...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="714">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"It is just as it is with the flower.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– C’est comme pour la fleur.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="715">
  <src xml:lang="EN">If you love a flower that lives on a star, it is sweet to look at the sky at night.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Si tu aimes une fleur qui se trouve dans une étoile, c’est doux, la nuit, de regarder le ciel.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="716">
  <src xml:lang="EN">All the stars are a-bloom with flowers...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Toutes les étoiles sont fleuries.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-3" id="717">
  <src xml:lang="EN">"Yes, I know...”<br/>"It is just as it is with the water.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr…<br/>– 98 –<br/>– C’est comme pour l’eau.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="718">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Because of the pulley, and the rope, what you gave me to drink was like music.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Celle que tu m’as donnée à boire était comme une musique, à cause de la poulie et de la corde… tu te rappelles… elle était bonne.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-4" id="719">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You remember, how good it was.”<br/>"Yes, I know...”<br/>"And at night you will look up at the stars.<br/>Where I live everything is so small that I cannot show you where my star is to be found.<br/>It is better, like that.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Bien sûr…<br/>– Tu regarderas, la nuit, les étoiles.<br/>C’est trop petit chez moi pour que je te montre où se trouve la mienne.<br/>C’est mieux comme ça.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="720">
  <src xml:lang="EN">My star will just be one of the stars, for you.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mon étoile, ça sera pour toi une des étoiles.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="13-10" id="721">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And so you will love to watch all the stars in the heavens... they will all be your friends.<br/>And, besides, I am going to make you a present...”<br/>He laughed again.<br/>"Ah, little prince, dear little prince!<br/>I love to hear that laughter!”<br/>"That is my present.<br/>Just that. It will be as it was when we drank the water...”<br/>"What are you trying to say?”<br/>"All men have the stars,” he answered, "but they are not the same things for different people.<br/>For some, who are travellers, the stars are guides.<br/>For others they are no more than little lights in the sky.<br/>For others, who are scholars, they are problems.<br/>For my businessman they were wealth.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors, toutes les étoiles, tu aimeras les regarder… Elles seront toutes tes amies.<br/>Et puis je vais te faire un cadeau… Il rit encore.<br/>– Ah ! petit bonhomme, petit bonhomme j’aime entendre ce rire !<br/>– Justement ce sera mon cadeau… ce sera comme pour l’eau…<br/>– Que veux-tu dire ?<br/>– Les gens ont des étoiles qui ne sont pas les mêmes.<br/>Pour les uns, qui voyagent, les étoiles sont des guides.<br/>Pour d’autres elles ne sont rien que de petites lumières.<br/>Pour d’autres, qui sont savants, elles sont des problèmes.<br/>Pour mon businessman elles étaient de l’or.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="722">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But all these stars are silent.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais toutes ces étoiles-là se taisent.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="7-6" id="723">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You, you alone, will have the stars as no one else has them”<br/>"What are you trying to say?”<br/>"In one of the stars I shall be living.<br/>In one of them I shall be laughing.<br/>And so it will be as if all the stars were laughing, when you look at the sky at night... you, only you, will have stars that can laugh!”<br/>And he laughed again.<br/>"And when your sorrow is comforted (time soothes all sorrows) you will be content that you have known me.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Toi, tu auras des étoiles comme personne n’en a…<br/>– Que veux-tu dire ?<br/>– Quand tu regarderas le ciel, la nuit, puisque j’habiterai dans l’une d’elles, puisque je rirai dans l’une d’elles, alors ce sera pour toi comme si riaient toutes les étoiles.<br/>Tu auras, toi, des étoiles qui savent rire !<br/>Et il rit encore.<br/>– Et quand tu seras consolé (on se console toujours) tu seras content de m’avoir connu.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="724">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You will always be my friend.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu seras toujours mon ami.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="725">
  <src xml:lang="EN">You will want to laugh with me.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu auras envie de rire avec moi.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="726">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And you will sometimes open your window, so, for that pleasure... and your friends will be properly astonished to see you laughing as you look up at the sky!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et tu ouvriras parfois ta fenêtre, comme ça, pour le plaisir… Et tes amis seront bien étonnés de te voir rire en regardant le ciel.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="727">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then you will say to them, ‘Yes, the stars always make me laugh!’</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors tu leur diras : ' Oui, les étoiles, ça me fait toujours rire !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="26-23" id="728">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And they will think you are crazy.<br/>It will be a very shabby trick that I shall have played on you...”<br/>And he laughed again.<br/>"It will be as if, in place of the stars, I had given you a great number of little bells that knew how to laugh...”<br/>And he laughed again.<br/>Then he quickly became serious: "Tonight, you know... do not come,” said the little prince.<br/>"I shall not leave you,” I said.<br/>"I shall look as if I were suffering.<br/>I shall look a little as if I were dying.<br/>It is like that.<br/>Do not come to see that.<br/>It is not worth the trouble...”<br/>"I shall not leave you.”<br/>But he was worried.<br/>"I tell you, it is also because of the snake.<br/>He must not bite you.<br/>Snakes, they<br/>are malicious creatures.<br/>This one might bite you just for fun...”<br/>"I shall not leave you.”<br/>But a thought came to reassure him: "It is true that they have no more poison for a second bite.”<br/>That night I did not see him set out on his way.<br/>He got away from me without making a sound.<br/>When I succeeded in catching up with him he was walking along with a quick and resolute step.<br/>He said to me merely: "Ah!<br/>You are there...”<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">' Et ils te croiront fou.<br/>Je t’aurai joué un bien vilain tour… Et il rit encore.<br/>– Ce sera comme si je t’avais donné, au lieu d’étoiles, des tas de petits grelots qui savent rire… Et il rit encore.<br/>Puis il redevint sérieux :<br/>– Cette nuit… tu sais… ne viens pas.<br/>– Je ne te quitterai pas.<br/>– J’aurai l’air d’avoir mal… j’aurai un peu l’air de mourir.<br/>C’est comme ça.<br/>Ne viens pas voir ça, ce n’est pas la peine…<br/>– Je ne te quitterai pas.<br/>Mais il était soucieux.<br/>– Je te dis ça… c’est à cause aussi du serpent.<br/>Il ne faut pas qu’il te morde… Les serpents, c’est méchant.<br/>Ça peut mordre pour le plaisir…<br/>– Je ne te quitterai pas.<br/>Mais quelque chose le rassura :<br/>– C’est vrai qu’ils n’ont plus de venin pour la seconde morsure… Cette nuit-là je ne le vis pas se mettre en route.<br/>Il s’était évadé sans bruit.<br/>Quand je réussis à le rejoindre il marchait décidé, d’un pas rapide.<br/>Il me dit seulement :<br/>– Ah ! tu es là… Et il me prit par la main.<br/>Mais il se tourmenta encore :<br/>– Tu as eu tort.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="729">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And he took me by the hand.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tu auras de la peine.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="7-4" id="730">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he was still worrying.<br/>"It was wrong of you to come.<br/>You will suffer.<br/>I shall look as if I were dead; and that will not be true...”<br/>I said nothing.<br/>"You understand... it is too far.<br/>I cannot carry this body with me.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">J’aurai l’air d’être mort et ce ne sera pas vrai… Moi je me taisais.<br/>– Tu comprends.<br/>C’est trop loin.<br/>Je ne peux pas emporter ce corps-là.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="731">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is too heavy.”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est trop lourd.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-4" id="732">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I said nothing.<br/>"But it will be like an old abandoned shell.<br/>There is nothing sad about old shells...”<br/>I said nothing.<br/>He was a little discouraged.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Moi je me taisais.<br/>– Mais ce sera comme une vieille écorce abandonnée.<br/>Ce n’est pas triste les vieilles écorces… Moi je me taisais.<br/>Il se découragea un peu.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="733">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But he made one more effort: "You know, it will be very nice.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais il fit encore un effort :</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="734">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I, too, shall look at the stars.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">– Ce sera gentil, tu sais.<br/>Moi aussi je regarderai les étoiles.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="735">
  <src xml:lang="EN">All the stars will be wells with a rusty pulley.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Toutes les étoiles seront des puits avec une poulie rouillée.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="20-18" id="736">
  <src xml:lang="EN">All the stars will pour out fresh water for me to drink...”<br/>I said nothing.<br/>"That will be so amusing!<br/>You will have five hundred million little bells, and I shall have five hundred million springs of fresh water...”<br/>And he too said nothing more, because he was crying...<br/>"Here it is. Let me go on by myself.”<br/>And he sat down, because he was afraid.<br/>Then he said, again: "You know, my flower...<br/>I am responsible for her.<br/>And she is so weak!<br/>She has four thorns, of no use at all, to protect herself against all the world...”<br/>I too sat down, because I was not able to stand up any longer.<br/>"There now, that is all...”<br/>He still hesitated a little; then he got up.<br/>He took one step.<br/>I could not move.<br/>There was nothing but a flash of yellow close to his ankle.<br/>He remained motionless for an instant.<br/>He did not cry out.<br/>He fell as gently as a tree falls.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Toutes les étoiles me verseront à boire… Moi je me taisais.<br/>– Ce sera tellement amusant !<br/>Tu auras cinq cents millions de grelots, j’aurai cinq cents millions de fontaines… Et il se tut aussi, parce qu’il pleurait…<br/>– C’est là. Laisse-moi faire un pas tout seul.<br/>Et il s’assit parce qu’il avait peur.<br/>Il dit encore :<br/>– Tu sais… ma fleur… j’en suis responsable !<br/>Et elle est tellement faible !<br/>Et elle est tellement naïve.<br/>Elle a quatre épines de rien du tout pour la protéger contre le monde… Moi je m’assis parce que je ne pouvais plus me tenir debout.<br/>Il dit :<br/>– Voilà… C’est tout… Il hésita encore un peu, puis il se releva.<br/>Il fit un pas.<br/>Moi je ne pouvais pas bouger.<br/>Il n’y eut rien qu’un éclair jaune près de sa cheville.<br/>Il demeura un instant immobile.<br/>Il ne cria pas.<br/>Il tomba doucement comme tombe un arbre.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="737">
  <src xml:lang="EN">There was not even any sound, because of the sand.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça ne fit même pas de bruit, à cause du sable.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="738">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And now six years have already gone by...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et maintenant, bien sûr, ça fait six ans déjà… Je n’ai jamais encore raconté cette histoire.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="6-5" id="739">
  <src xml:lang="EN">I have never yet told this story.<br/>The companions who met me on my return were well content to see me alive.<br/>I was sad, but I told them: "I am tired.”<br/>Now my sorrow is comforted a little.<br/>That is to say, not entirely.<br/>But I know that he did go back to his planet, because I did not find his body at daybreak.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Les camarades qui m’ont revu ont été bien contents de me revoir vivant.<br/>J’étais triste mais je leur disais : ' C’est la fatigue… '<br/>Maintenant je me suis un peu consolé.<br/>C’est-à-dire… pas tout à fait.<br/>Mais je sais bien qu’il est revenu à sa planète, car, au lever du jour, je n’ai pas retrouvé son corps.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="740">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It was not such a heavy body... and at night I love to listen to the stars.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ce n’était pas un corps tellement lourd… Et j’aime la nuit écouter les étoiles.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="741">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is like five hundred million little bells...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est comme cinq cent millions de grelots…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-2" id="742">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But there is one extraordinary thing... when I drew the muzzle for the little prince, I forgot to add the leather strap to it.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Mais voilà qu’il se passe quelque chose d’extraordinaire.<br/>La muselière que j’ai dessinée pour le petit prince, j’ai oublié d’y ajouter la courroie de cuir !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="743">
  <src xml:lang="EN">He will never have been able to fasten it on his sheep.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il n’aura jamais pu l’attacher au mouton.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="744">
  <src xml:lang="EN">So now I keep wondering: what is happening on his planet?</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Alors je me demande : ' Que s’est-il passé sur sa planète ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="745">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Perhaps the sheep has eaten the flower...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Peut-être bien que le mouton a mangé la fleur… '</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="746">
  <src xml:lang="EN">At one time I say to myself: "Surely not!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tantôt je me dis : ' Sûrement non !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="747">
  <src xml:lang="EN">The little prince shuts his flower under her glass globe every night, and he watches over his sheep very carefully...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Le petit prince enferme sa fleur toutes les nuits sous son globe de verre, et il surveille bien son mouton… ' Alors je suis heureux.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="2-1" id="748">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Then I am happy.<br/>And there is sweetness in the laughter of all the stars.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et toutes les étoiles rient doucement.<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="749">
  <src xml:lang="EN">But at another time I say to myself: "At some moment or other one is absent-minded, and that is enough!</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Tantôt je me dis : ' On est distrait une fois ou l’autre, et ça suffit !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="750">
  <src xml:lang="EN">On some one evening he forgot the glass globe, or the sheep got out, without making any noise, in the night...”</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Il a oublié, un soir, le globe de verre, ou bien le mouton est sorti sans bruit pendant la nuit… ' Alors les grelots se changent tous en larmes !</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="751">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And then the little bells are changed to tears...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="752">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Here, then, is a great mystery.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est là un bien grand mystère.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="753">
  <src xml:lang="EN">For you who also love the little prince, and for me, nothing in the universe can be the same if somewhere, we do not know where, a sheep that we never saw has eaten a rose...</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Pour vous qui aimez aussi le petit prince, comme pour moi, rien de l’univers n’est semblable si quelque part, on ne sait où, un mouton que nous ne connaissons pas a, oui ou non, mangé une rose…</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="754">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Look up at the sky.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Regardez le ciel.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="755">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Ask yourselves: is it yes or no?</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Demandez-vous : le mouton oui ou non a- t-il mangé la fleur ?</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="3-2" id="756">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Has the sheep eaten the flower?<br/>And you will see how everything changes...<br/>And no grown-up will ever understand that this is a matter of so much importance!<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et vous verrez comme tout change…<br/>Et aucune grande personne ne comprendra jamais que ça a tellement d’importance !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="757">
  <src xml:lang="EN">This is, to me, the loveliest and saddest landscape in the world.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ça c’est, pour moi, le plus beau et le plus triste paysage du monde.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="758">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is the same as that on the preceding page, but I have drawn it again to impress it on your memory.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est le même paysage que celui de la page précédente, mais je l’ai dessiné une fois encore pour bien vous le montrer.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="759">
  <src xml:lang="EN">It is here that the little prince appeared on Earth, and disappeared.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">C’est ici que le petit prince a apparu sur terre, puis disparu.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="760">
  <src xml:lang="EN">Look at it carefully so that you will be sure to recognise it in case you travel some day to the African desert.</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Regardez attentivement ce paysage afin d’être sûrs de le reconnaître, si vous voyagez un jour en Afrique, dans le désert.</tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="5-3" id="761">
  <src xml:lang="EN">And, if you should come upon this spot, please do not hurry on.<br/>Wait for a time, exactly under the star.<br/>Then, if a little man appears who laughs, who has golden hair and who refuses to answer questions, you will know who he is.<br/>If this should happen, please comfort me.<br/>Send me word that he has come back.<br/></src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Et, s’il vous arrive de passer par là, je vous en supplie, ne vous pressez pas, attendez un peu juste sous l’étoile !<br/>Si alors un enfant vient à vous, s’il rit, s’il a des cheveux d’or, s’il ne répond pas quand on l’interroge, vous devinerez bien qui il est.<br/>Alors soyez gentils !<br/></tgt>
</seg>
<seg  match="1-1" id="762">
  <src xml:lang="EN">END</src>
  <tgt xml:lang="FR">Ne me laissez pas tellement triste : écrivez-moi vite qu’il est revenu…</tgt>
</seg>
</segments>
</bitext>
